<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Churches authority asserted in a sermon preached at Chelmsford, at the metropoliticall visitation of the most Reverend Father in God, VVilliam, Lord Arch-bishop of Canterbury his Grace, &amp;c. March 1. 1636. By Samuel Hoard B.D. and Parson of Morton in Essex.</title>
            <author>Hoard, Samuel, 1599-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03409</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13533</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104116</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839855</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839855</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4314</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03409)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4314)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1242:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Churches authority asserted in a sermon preached at Chelmsford, at the metropoliticall visitation of the most Reverend Father in God, VVilliam, Lord Arch-bishop of Canterbury his Grace, &amp;c. March 1. 1636. By Samuel Hoard B.D. and Parson of Morton in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Hoard, Samuel, 1599-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M[iles] F[lesher] for John Clark, and are to be sold at his shop under S. Peters Church in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC XXXVII. [1637]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>F3 is a cancel, with verso lines 25-26 having phrase "who dote .. their owne: as". Variant: with cancellandum lacking this phrase.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4314:1"/>
            <p>THE CHVRCHES AVTHORITY ASSERTED: <hi>IN</hi> A SERMON Preached at <hi>Chelmsford,</hi> at the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politicall Viſitation of the moſt Reverend Father in God, VVILLIAM, Lord Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> his Grace, &amp;c. <hi>March</hi> 1. 1636.</p>
            <p>BY SAMUEL HOARD B. D. and Parſon of <hi>Morton</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEB: 13.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves: for they watch for your ſoules, as they that muſt give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; that they may doe it with joy, and not with griefe; for that is unprofitable for you.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> for JOHN CLARK, and are to be ſold at his Shop under S. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>MDCXXXVII.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4314:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4314:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian and courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O Sweet a thing is <hi>Peace,</hi> that God is pleaſed to put it into his owne <hi>title,</hi> and to ſtyle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Peace:</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23. Nay, <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Love it ſelfe,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.16. and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce him that <hi>ſeekes</hi> and <hi>makes</hi> peace, a <hi>bleſſed man; Bleſſed are the Peace-makers, Mat</hi> 5.9. But much more amiable is the peace of the <hi>Church;</hi> being the principall thing that our bleſſed <hi>Sauiour,</hi> next to mans peace with <hi>God,</hi> came into the world to procure, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.15. and that which makes Gods <hi>family</hi> on earth like to the State of innocency in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and of <hi>glory</hi> in heaven. This peace therefore ſhould every <hi>ſonne</hi> of <hi>peace</hi> pray for, <hi>Pray for the peace of Jeruſalem, Pſal.</hi> 112. and purſue with all endeavour poſſible, as men doe their <hi>game,</hi> for ſo the word may ſignifie, <hi>Hob.</hi> 12.16. Follow peace with all men. But what <hi>peace</hi> can be expected without <hi>unity?</hi> like <hi>Hypocrates</hi> twins they decay and thrive, live and die together.</p>
            <p>And therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> puts them both together, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.3. <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace:</hi> and for the procuring of agreement in affections, he conjures the <hi>Philippians</hi> by all the arguments enforcing <hi>concord</hi> among Chriſtians, to a <hi>conſent</hi> of judgement, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>To be of one minde, Phil.</hi> 2.2. to beleeve and think the ſame thing. And therefore it ſhould be every mans care (contrary to the cuſtome of too many <hi>turbulent</hi> diſpoſitions, who can fiſh beſt in <hi>troubled</hi> waters, and gaine moſt <hi>profit</hi> or <hi>reſpect</hi> to themſelves by kindling <hi>contentions</hi> among brethren: not only to <hi>marke them that cauſe diviſions, and avoide them, Rom.</hi> 16.17. but <hi>fix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pede,</hi> with a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led reſolution and courage to <hi>oppoſe</hi> them, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> did S. <hi>Peter, Gal.</hi> 2. when he ſaw that he did not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>walk with a right foot,</hi> and take a right courſe for the uniting of the <hi>mindes,</hi> and by conſequent, the <hi>hearts</hi> of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles.</hi> As therefore it hath alwayes been my <hi>deſire,</hi> that we who are of the ſame <hi>ſaith,</hi> might be (if poſſible) in all things of the ſame <hi>opinion,</hi> ſo I thought it my <hi>duty</hi> at this time, having ſo faire an occaſion, by the command of my ſuperiours, to preach the <hi>Viſitation</hi> Sermon, put into my hands, to caſt in my <hi>mite</hi> toward the purchaſing of this <hi>pearle,</hi> and to ſet one ſmall <hi>prop</hi> under the houſe and <hi>Church</hi> of God in our Iſrael, too much <hi>tottering</hi> by our mutuall diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and for that end to <hi>juſtifie</hi> the <hi>authority</hi> of our Church, in requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:4314:3"/> an <hi>uniforme</hi> ſubjection in <hi>judgement</hi> and <hi>practiſe</hi> at the hands of her children to the comely and good <hi>orders</hi> therein eſtabliſhed, and to <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade</hi> a generall <hi>good opinion</hi> of, and <hi>obedience</hi> to her juſt authority in theſe things. Some there be ſo <hi>obſtinate</hi> in their error and undutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that like <hi>Solomons</hi> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, though they be brayed in a <hi>morter,</hi> and ſufficiently convinced of their falſe and diſorderly opinions and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, will not leave their folly: others there be, I hope, of more <hi>tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chable</hi> and <hi>tractable</hi> tempers, and willing, if better informed, to frame their courſes to more <hi>moderation</hi> and ſubjection. Now, <hi>ſermons</hi> of this <hi>nature</hi> may be of uſe to both theſe: to the <hi>firſt,</hi> to take off their <hi>fig-leaves,</hi> and preſent them naked (as troublers of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) to the deſerved <hi>ſtroke</hi> of juſtice: to the reſt, to make them <hi>peaceable</hi> members of the <hi>body</hi> wherein they live, and obedient children to the <hi>heads</hi> by whom they are governed. Whether I ſhall effect this <hi>laſt</hi> and <hi>beſt</hi> end of ſuch diſcourſes by preaching or printing this ſmall peece, I know not: I doe not altogether deſpaire: the <hi>former</hi> (I doubt not) I ſhall in ſome meaſure compaſſe: at leaſt <hi>liberabo animam meam,</hi> I ſhall hereby diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge mine owne <hi>conſcience,</hi> and <hi>famam meam,</hi> redeeme (in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree) my <hi>reputation</hi> too: Words being then moſt liable to envious miſtakes and miſ-reports, when they are but taken in by the <hi>eares</hi> of ſome few <hi>partiall</hi> and prejudging hearers, not expoſed to the <hi>eyes</hi> and <hi>view</hi> of more <hi>indifferent</hi> and charitably minded <hi>Readers.</hi> Bring an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and <hi>peaceable</hi> ſpirit with thee, and then <hi>reade,</hi> and <hi>cenſure</hi> as thou ſeeſt cauſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sa: Hoard.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>REcenſui concionem hane, cui titulus eſt <hi>[The Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Authority aſſerted]</hi> in qua nihil reperio quò mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſummâ cum utilitato Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>March 28. 1637.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>SA: BAKER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4314:3"/>
            <head>THE CHVRCHES AVTHORITIE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 COR. 14.40.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Let all things be done decently, and in order.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F the <hi>Devils</hi> practiſes againſt the <hi>Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Cohae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Text.</note> which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our gives notice of, Mat. 13.25. <hi>while men ſlept, the enemy came and ſowed tares among the wheat, and went his way;</hi> the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were too true an <hi>example.</hi> For no ſooner had S. <hi>Paul</hi> (after much paines taken to ſowe the good <hi>ſeed</hi> of ſaving truth among them, and to make them one of <hi>Chriſts cornfields</hi>) departed from them to plow up other grounds, to plant other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but the <hi>enemy</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his deare Church, began to ſow the <hi>tares</hi> of ungodlineſſe among them, which (as ill weeds for the moſt part doe) ſprang up apace.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:4314:4"/>
            <p>For they became 1. <hi>Sectaries,</hi> dividing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves among <hi>Chriſt, Apollos, Paul,</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.11, 12. and making <hi>men</hi> the <hi>Lords</hi> of their faith and conſciences, which they ſhould have captivated to <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone.</p>
            <p n="2">2 They were <hi>Heretiques,</hi> denying a <hi>fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall</hi> Article, the <hi>Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Polluters</hi> alſo of Gods ſacred <hi>worſhip</hi> and <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances:</hi> Firſt, by their baſe <hi>indecencies; Their wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſate before God with their heads uncovered,</hi> and <hi>the men with their hats on:</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.4, 5: they min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled <hi>intemperate</hi> and carouſing <hi>bankets</hi> with the ſpirituall <hi>feaſt of the bleſſed Euchariſt, ver.</hi> 21: their <hi>women,</hi> beyond the modeſty that becomes that ſexe, <hi>preſumed to chat and talke their ſhares in the congregation, c.</hi> 14.34.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By their <hi>diſorders</hi> likewiſe; for they received not the <hi>holy Communion together,</hi> but by <hi>ſnatches, one before another came, cap</hi> 11.33: they <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſed unſeaſonable queſtions,</hi> while their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters were preaching, and rudely interrupted them, in their diſcourſe: <hi>cap</hi> 14.29.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, By their empty and <hi>unprofitable aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies;</hi> for their <hi>trumpets made an uncertaine ſound,</hi> they <hi>prayed</hi> in their <hi>Churches</hi> in a <hi>tongue they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe were great ſcandalls.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.11.</note>The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> therefore being informed by ſome of <hi>Cloes</hi> family, of their declined condition, like a loving <hi>paſtor</hi> labours to remove theſe <hi>tares,</hi> and reduce this Church to its <hi>primitive</hi> purity. For the procuring of which hee takes a mixt courſe,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4314:4"/> that they might neither <hi>deteſt</hi> his <hi>ſeverity,</hi> nor yet <hi>deſpiſe</hi> his <hi>lenity.</hi> One while he ſharply <hi>reprooveth,</hi> another while he gently <hi>allureth;</hi> in one place hee <hi>puniſheth,</hi> in another he <hi>preſcribeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Chapter hee meeteth with two faults, <hi>diſorder,</hi> and <hi>unprofitableneſſe:</hi> and becauſe <hi>contraria contrariis curantur, diſtempers are uſually cured by remedies of a contrary nature;</hi> for the healing of their <hi>unprofitableneſſe</hi> in the uſe of their religious exerciſes, he command, that all things bee done to <hi>edification, ver.</hi> 26: and for the removall of their <hi>indecencies</hi> and <hi>diſorders;</hi> he requires that all things be done <hi>decently</hi> and in <hi>order.</hi> And ſo I am come to my Text.</p>
            <p>In which (by the judgement of expoſitors) St. <hi>Paul inveſteth</hi> the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſcope and parts of the Text, and the point inſiſted on.</note> and in them all Chriſtian <hi>Churches,</hi> with authority to ordaine <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> appertaining to <hi>order</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency</hi> in the ſervice of God <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <p>Hinc appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret liberum eſse Eccleſus, titus ordinare ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes ordini &amp; decoro.</p>
                  <p>Heming in hunc locum.</p>
               </note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Hinc aparet</hi> (ſaith Hemingius) hence it appeareth, that it is in the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Churches to ordaine rites ſerving to order and comelineſſe. <note n="(b)" place="margin">Facit Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>teſtatem de decoro, et ordine eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtico liberò diſponendi, et leges ferendi. <hi>Par in hunc loc.</hi>
                  </note> Facit Eccleſiae poteſtatem &amp;c. He gives the Church <hi>(ſaith Pareus)</hi> power, freely to diſpoſe of things belonging to Eccleſiaſticall order and decency. <note n="(c)" place="margin">Non poteſt haberi, quod Paulus hic exigit, ut decenter omnia, et ordine fiant, niſi additis conſtitutionibus, tanquam vinculis quibusda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ordo ipſe et decorum ſervetur. <hi>Cal. Inſtit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> Non poteſt haberi, &amp;c. That which St. Paul requires <hi>(ſaith Calvin)</hi> cannot be had, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe there bee Canons made, by which, as by certaine bands, men and things may bee kept together in a comely order.</q> 
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Davenant. de Iudic. Cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. fidei c. <hi>16.</hi> p. <hi>84.</hi>
               </note> And the Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> having delivered a poſition, that the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4314:5"/> 
               <hi>Prelates of the Church have power to appoint rites and ceremonies reſpecting the externall policy of the Church, prooveth it by my text, Let all things be done decently, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words therefore in the opinion of theſe men, and almoſt all writers on theſe words or point, containe the <hi>Churches Inveſtiture:</hi> and may be caſt into theſe two parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Churches <hi>liberty, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, let all things be done.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The Churches <hi>limits, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, decently and in order.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Or elſe into theſe two.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Her <hi>Authority</hi> to make laws, <hi>Let &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The <hi>object</hi> about which her Authority is to move, matters of order and decency, <hi>decently, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>From both theſe ariſeth the <hi>point,</hi> on which I purpoſe to build my preſent diſcourſe, and which I will deliver in the words of our <hi>twentieth Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, — That the Church hath power to decree Rites and Ceremonies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of this concluſion, 1. I will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine the <hi>termes.</hi> 2. Prove the <hi>point.</hi> 3. Touch upon ſuch <hi>conſectartes,</hi> as the point doth naturally derive it ſelfe into. Of all theſe with what brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I can.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The termes explained. what is meant by Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Rites.</note>The <hi>termes</hi> are two, the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ceremonies</hi> are externall <hi>acts</hi> and <hi>adjuncts</hi> anne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed to ſacred Services.</p>
            <p>For in <hi>Religion</hi> there are two things conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; <hi>Subſtantialls,</hi> and <hi>Circumſtantialls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Subſtantialls</hi> are of two ſorts.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:4314:5"/>1. Matters of <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>manners,</hi> to be beleeved and done of neceſſity to ſalvation, conteined in the Creed and ten Commandements.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sacraments</hi> ordained, for the <hi>bringing</hi> of men and women into the Church, and their <hi>conduct</hi> therein to everlaſting happineſſe. About theſe the power which the Church hath, is, to preſerve them (as the <hi>Ark</hi> did the tables of the <hi>Law</hi>) to give an honorable <hi>teſtimony</hi> to them, to <hi>conſecrate,</hi> to <hi>diſpenſe</hi> them to her children, and to <hi>tranſmit</hi> them to poſterity; in which reſpects ſhe is called, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Pillar,</hi> and <hi>ground</hi> of truth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. Power to <hi>make, adde, alter,</hi> or <hi>diminiſh</hi> theſe ſhe never had. Never durſt any <hi>Prelates</hi> in the Church, but the <hi>Pope,</hi> take liberty to ſtamp <hi>new Articles</hi> of faith, or to joyne <hi>Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to the writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> word of God, for ſupply of its im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection, which are of the ſame authority,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 4. <hi>decre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1</note> and to be received <hi>(pari pietatis affectu) with the like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious reſpect,</hi> as the <hi>Trent</hi> Councill hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined: never did any preſume, but he, to <hi>curt all</hi> the <hi>Lords</hi> Supper, by taking away the cup from the people, or to <hi>transforme</hi> the <hi>Sacrament</hi> into a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> propitiatory for quick and dead, to the great injury of that alſufficient Sacrifice once of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered upon the Croſſe by our Lord himſelfe.</p>
            <p>In all theſe, <hi>manum de tabula,</hi> hands off: for they are all above the <hi>Churches</hi> power.</p>
            <p>But, Secondly, there are beſides theſe, ſome <hi>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonialls</hi> and <hi>circumſtantialls,</hi> neceſſary for the right <hi>ordering</hi> and cariage of Gods ſervice, the <hi>trayning</hi> up of people in piety, and the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4314:6"/> of religion: for <hi>without ceremonies</hi> (ſaith Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy) <note n="(a)" place="margin">Sine Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, nec ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deles in unum convenne &amp; co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leſcere poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt, nec Deo publice ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vire. <hi>Zanch de Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. l</hi> 1. <hi>p</hi> 420.</note> 
               <hi>neither could the faithfull grow up together into one body, nor give God any publique worſhip.</hi> That God is to be worſhipped by his owne rule, and with his owne preſcribed acts and dutyes of religion, is <hi>Subſtance;</hi> but that this may bee well done, ſome circumſtances of <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>place, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, geſtures, habites, &amp;c.</hi> muſt bee determined. What therefore ſhall be the <hi>times,</hi> wherein Gods people muſt come together to worſhip him, and how farre they are to be <hi>ſanctified;</hi> what are to be the <hi>places,</hi> wherein wee are to meet, and how to be <hi>adorned;</hi> in what <hi>order</hi> divine <hi>Service</hi> ſhall be celebrated; with what <hi>habit</hi> the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> when he commeth to miniſter before the Lord, ſhould be clothed; what <hi>geſtures</hi> of body, both <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>people</hi> ſhall uſe in their publique devotions; and the <hi>times</hi> when this or that particular <hi>geſture</hi> of kneeling, ſtanding, ſitting, or bowing may be uſed with moſt comelineſſe and profit; what kinde of <hi>places</hi> are fitteſt for <hi>Service</hi> and <hi>Sermon;</hi> what <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> what <hi>chalices,</hi> what other <hi>ornaments</hi> doe beſt beſeem that ſacred myſtery of the Lords Supper, &amp;c: Theſe, and ſuch like circumſtances, are the things permitted to the <hi>Churches</hi> liberty to <hi>deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What we are to underſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by Church.</note>By <hi>Church,</hi> (which is my ſecond <hi>terme</hi>) I meane; not <hi>private</hi> and inferior members of the Church, whoſe place is obedience, not government: for we ſhould have a <hi>mad</hi> Church, and a <hi>miſerable</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſervice, if every private ſpirit might have authority to order theſe things, as hee thinkes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4314:6"/> good. It would be (I feare me) like that <hi>miſ-ſhapen</hi> Picture, which the Painter <hi>Polycletes</hi> made by the peoples direction, a very deformed one: a <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Service,</hi> that could not be knowne or acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for ſuch, except a man ſhould write upon it, (as under ſome rude draughts men uſe to doe) <hi>this is a church;</hi> or ſet a <hi>cryer,</hi> when people are worſhipping God in his Houſe, to <hi>proclaime</hi> and ſay, <hi>this is divine Service.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by <hi>Church</hi> I meane, the Churches <hi>Pilots,</hi> who ſit at the ſterne, and are by their office to guide the <hi>Ship</hi> of the <hi>church</hi> through the Sea of this world to the haven of eternall happineſſe: thoſe whom the Apoſtle calleth <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Biſhops, and <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and watchmen of the Lords army. For, as head and members divide the body <hi>naturall,</hi> and the <hi>members,</hi> with <hi>all</hi> things belonging to their comelineſſe and welfare, are ordered by the <hi>head,</hi> and could not bee diſpoſed of by the members without a ſchiſme in the body, 1 Cor. 12: ſo, heads and members divide all bodyes, <hi>civill,</hi> and <hi>eccleſiaſticall;</hi> and whatſoever is to bee done for matter of direction and government, hath alwaies beene, and muſt bee the ſole prerogative of the <hi>heads</hi> of theſe bodyes, unleſſe wee will have all <hi>common wealths</hi> and <hi>churches</hi> broken all to peeces.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come from the <hi>termes</hi> to the <hi>point.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The power of the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> is dignified with the name of <hi>Sword, Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>Hee heareth not the ſword in vaine:</hi> the authority of the <hi>Church</hi> with the name of <hi>keyes,</hi> Mat. 16. <hi>To thee will I give the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4314:7"/> keyes of the Kingdome of Heaven.</hi> Theſe <hi>keyes</hi> are twofold.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A <hi>Key</hi> of <hi>order,</hi> which is the priviledge of the <hi>whole</hi> Prieſthood, and it is an <hi>Authority</hi> of <hi>admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring</hi> the word and Sacraments, of <hi>remitting</hi> and <hi>retaining</hi> ſinnes, <hi>in interiori foro,</hi> in the Court of Conſcience.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A <hi>Key</hi> of <hi>Iuriſdiction,</hi> which is, a <hi>power</hi> of <hi>bin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding</hi> and <hi>looſing</hi> men, <hi>in Foro exteriori,</hi> in the courts of juſtice; and of making <hi>lawes</hi> and orders for the government of Gods houſe. And this is peculiar to the <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, 1. by <hi>examples,</hi> 2. by <hi>conſent</hi> of writers, 3. by <hi>reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Proved by examples of the Apoſtles.</note>1. It appeares by <hi>Examples</hi> both of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> and Churches of God, who have in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall generations put this Authority into <hi>execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It ſeemeth good to the Holy Ghoſt and to us, to lay upon you no greater burthen than theſe neceſſary things; that ye abſtaine from meats offered to Idolls, and from blood, and from things ſtrangled, and from fornication,</hi> ſay the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in their letter to the <hi>Gentiles, Acts</hi> 15.28. In which words we ſee, 1. That they <hi>make</hi> a <hi>Canon,</hi> 2. That this <hi>Canon</hi> was concerning abſtinence from ſome things that were <hi>indifferent,</hi> (for ſuch were thoſe <hi>Idolothytes,</hi> things <hi>ſtrangled,</hi> &amp; <hi>blood</hi>) 3. That they <hi>uſurped</hi> not this authority, but had it from the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> whom therefore they joyne with themſelves in their letter as Preſident of their Commiſſion, <hi>It ſeemeth good to the Holy Ghoſt and to us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor did they exerciſe this power onely when
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4314:7"/> they ſate in the Councill together, but when they were aſunder alſo; for St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth often menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>conſtitutions</hi> that hee made for divers Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. For the Churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> hee made an <hi>order,</hi> That <hi>collections</hi> ſhould bee made for the poore on every firſt day of the weeke; and meant to bring in the ſame cuſtome into the <hi>Corinthian</hi> Church, 1 Cor. 16.1, 2.</p>
            <p>He framed ordinances for <hi>Corinth,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.2. <hi>viz:</hi> that <hi>women ſhould cover their heads,</hi> &amp; <hi>men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover theirs</hi> in the Church, <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7. that men ſhould not uſe <hi>long haire,</hi> but <hi>women</hi> ſhould, <hi>ver.</hi> 14, 15. that they ſhould tarry one for another when they come to receive the holy Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, <hi>v.</hi> 33. &amp;c. And hee <hi>commends</hi> that people for keeping thoſe his traditions, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. and <hi>promiſeth</hi> when he came againe, to diſpoſe of other things, which were not as yet well ſetled and ordered. <hi>ver.</hi> 34.</p>
            <p>Some alſo hee made for the government of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2.15. where hee exhorts them <hi>to hold faſt the traditions which he had taught them, both by word of mouth, and by letters;</hi> and 2 Theſſ. 3.14. where hee commandeth <hi>oppoſers</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his determinations to be <hi>excommunicated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But (perhaps) it will be ſaid, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> that <hi>their</hi> Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were of <hi>divine</hi> authority, becauſe they were <hi>Pen-men</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and did but <hi>convey</hi> thoſe conſtitutions to the Churches, which the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> did make and <hi>indite</hi> for their uſe.</p>
            <p>It is true, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſpake by inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and were imployed in writing downe Gods word for the good of the Church; but yet many
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4314:8"/> things they ſpake and did, not as <hi>Secretaryes</hi> to the Holy Ghoſt, but as ordinary <hi>Paſtors</hi> of the Church, <note n="(a)" place="margin">Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atenus erant ordinatii eccleſiae Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctores, de haſce titibus externis pro ſua ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia ſtatue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, quod ad aedificationem eccleſia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> facere videbatur. <hi>Dav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. l. de Jud. Cont. c.</hi> 16. <hi>rat.</hi> 2.</note> As appeareth moſt plainly by ſome ſpeeches which St. <hi>Paul</hi> lets fall in 1 Cor. 7. <hi>I ſpeake this by permiſsion, and not of commandement,</hi> ver. 6. To <hi>the marryed I command, yet not I, but the Lord,</hi> ver. 10. To the <hi>reſt ſpeake I, not the Lord,</hi> v. 12. <hi>Concerning Virgins I have no commandement of the Lord; I give my judgement as one that hath obtained mercy of the Lord to be faithfull. ver.</hi> 25. In all theſe paſſages, 1. He <hi>diſtinguiſheth</hi> betweene authority <hi>divine</hi> and <hi>humane.</hi> 2. He <hi>affirmeth,</hi> that he did ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>viſe and command many things by his own pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as a prudent <hi>paſtor</hi> of the Church, for which he had no expreſſe and <hi>particular</hi> command from the <hi>Lord.</hi> Now if he did by his owne authority preſcribe ſome things to be done for the guiding of people in point of manners and <hi>morality,</hi> much more did he take that <hi>liberty</hi> in point of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and <hi>ceremonies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">And of the Iewiſh and Chriſtian Churches.</note>To theſe examples of the bleſſed <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> I may joine the practice of the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Church; who though they had an externall forme of <hi>diſcipline</hi> preſcribed them, and all things belonging thereto, even to the <hi>pinnes</hi> and <hi>barres</hi> of the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> the <hi>broomes, aſhpans,</hi> and <hi>ſnuffers</hi> of the <hi>Sanctuary;</hi> yet they tooke liberty to <hi>adde</hi> ſome things which were not <hi>expreſſely</hi> commanded. They <hi>annointed</hi> their <hi>dead</hi> with odours, and our Saviour was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be buryed after that manner. The <hi>Rube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nits</hi> built an <hi>Altar</hi> on the bankes of <hi>Iordan, Ioſh.</hi> 22. which <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and the heads of the people permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4314:8"/> to ſtand. <hi>Solomon</hi> built an <hi>Altar</hi> of himſelfe by the <hi>brazen Altar,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.64. And (which comes nearer to our purpoſe) the Iewes did inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute two great <hi>Feſtivalls</hi> to be ſolemnized every yeare; the Feaſt of <hi>Purim</hi> in memory of their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from the bloody conſpiracy of <hi>Haman;</hi> and the feaſt of <hi>Dedication,</hi> for a memoriall of the Temples purification, after it had been polluted by King <hi>Antiochus.</hi> And this holy day ſet up by their <hi>own</hi> authority, our <hi>Saviour</hi> was ſo farre from diſliking, or reproving, that he was pleaſed to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour it with his gracious preſence, <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.22. The <hi>order</hi> alſo of their <hi>burials,</hi> and the rites of their <hi>mariage,</hi> were moſt, or all of them made by their <hi>owne</hi> diſcretion. Had theſe <hi>Iews,</hi> to whom God had given a <hi>perfit</hi> platforme, this liberty; and have not <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Churches, to whom no rule is in this caſe given, the ſame power in ſuch things, and a far greater?</p>
            <p>And this liberty have all the <hi>governours</hi> likewiſe of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> congregations uſed in their ſeverall Churches and ages, as I ſhall have occaſion to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate by and by: All which <hi>examples</hi> are an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>proofe</hi> of the Churches power in theſe exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ordinances: becauſe, 1. there is no <hi>Precept</hi> againſt theſe examples; for againſt an expreſſe command examples prove nothing. 2. The <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> were more faithfull ſervants to their Lord, than to <hi>intrench</hi> upon his royall <hi>prerogative,</hi> and more <hi>humble</hi> than to goe beyond the <hi>bounds</hi> of their commiſſion. 3. It cannot with reaſon bee imagined, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> would ſuffer his <hi>Church,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:4314:9"/> throughout all ages, to ſleep to ſecurely in ſo great an error.<note place="margin">The power of the Church proved by conſent of writers.</note> And therefore leaving this, I come to my <hi>ſecond argument</hi> for the proofe of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches power, [the <hi>Conſent of Writers</hi>] which is an argument beyond exception, and able of it ſelfe to put the point in hand out of all queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calvin,</hi> whom all Sectaries make their Oracle in their plea againſt Ceremonies, hath theſe words. <note n="(a)" place="margin">Calv Opuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. pag <hi>344.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ne quis nos calumnietur nimis moroſos, &amp;c. Let no man thinke or ſay that we are ſo ſevere and harſh, as to take away all liberty in externall rites; I here give all readers to underſtand, that I contend not about ceremonies reſpecting order and decency in the Church: Our diſpute is againſt thoſe acts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſome thinke that God is truly, and properly worſhipt. I deny that theſe are under the power of men.</hi> And in <note n="(b)" place="margin">Idem Inſtit. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> Sect. <hi>14</hi>
               </note> another place he ſaith, <hi>Ergo (inquies) nihil ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniale rudioribus dabitur, &amp;c? Therefore thou wilt ſay, ſhall nothing Ceremoniall be appointed for the inſtruction of the ruder ſort? I ſay not ſo, for I know well enough that all ſuch helps are profitable to them: only I contend, that in preſcribing them, ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and meaſure be uſed, as may illuſtrate, not obſcure Chriſt.</hi> And <note n="(c)" place="margin">Calv <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. Sect. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> in the ſame Chapter hee layes it downe for a concluſion: That <hi>Chriſt</hi> would not preſcribe particularly concerning ceremonies, what we ought to follow, but referre us to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of generall rules.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We hold</hi> (ſaith <hi>Perkins</hi>) <note n="(d)" place="margin">Perk. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſ. Cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ol. <hi>of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</hi> con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that the Church hath power to preſcribe ordinances, rules or traditions tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the time and place of Gods worſhip, and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning order and comelineſſe to be uſed in the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:4314:9"/>
            <p>Peruſe the <hi>Harmony</hi> of confeſſions, and ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be not the judgement of all thoſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. More particularly, for inſtance, take the <hi>Auſpurge</hi> confeſſion; <hi>Melancthon</hi> the contriver of it, directly for this power ſaith, <note n="(e)" place="margin">Aug. confeſ. Art. ult. &amp; Apol. ej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dem.</note> 
               <hi>Licet Paſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; Epiſcopis, &amp;c. It is lawfull for Biſhops and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors to make Canons, that things be done in order in the Church:</hi> and he proves it by S. <hi>Pauls</hi> example, <hi>Sic Paulus ordinat, &amp;c.</hi> So S <hi>Paul</hi> ordained, that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhould cover their heads, and <hi>confine</hi> their tongues in the congregation, &amp;c. Only ſome <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> he gives to this effect. 1. That theſe orders be not <hi>impoſed</hi> as <hi>parts</hi> of Gods worſhip. 2. That they be not <hi>urged</hi> as things <hi>neceſſary</hi> in themſelves. 3. That for their <hi>matter,</hi> they be not contrary to any Evangelicall truths; for <hi>if an Angell from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſhould preach unto us another Goſpell, wee are to hold him accurſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all which cautions, he doth not <hi>deny,</hi> or <hi>abridge</hi> the power of Church-governours in theſe matters, but only <hi>remember</hi> them how to uſe their liberty therein, to that end for which they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it, the <hi>glory</hi> of God, and the Churches <hi>edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> according to that ſpeech of S. <hi>Paul, This au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is given us for edification, and not for your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi> 2 Cor. 10.8.</p>
            <p>But what need I ſtand upon particular inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? Do we not all grant in our <hi>controverſie</hi> with Papiſts about <hi>traditions;</hi> that there are 2. ſorts of <hi>traditions, Apoſtolicall,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> and that both theſe are under the <hi>power</hi> of the Church?</p>
            <p n="1">1. We yeeld that there are <hi>Apoſtolique</hi> traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4314:10"/> 
               <hi>rituall</hi> and <hi>dogmaticall,</hi> which are no where <hi>mentioned,</hi> or not <hi>enjoyned</hi> in the Scriptures, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by word of mouth from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to their followers; for ſome of which theſe are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, <hi>viz.</hi> the number of <hi>Canonicall</hi> bookes, the Apoſtles <hi>Creed,</hi> the <hi>baptiſme of infants,</hi> the faſt of <hi>Lent,</hi> the <hi>Lords day,</hi> and the great feſtivals of <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſontide,</hi> Theſe we juſtly take for theirs, grounding upon S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> rule, <note n="(f)" place="margin">Quod uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa tenet ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia, nec con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s inſtitutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed ſemper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentum eſt, non niſi autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> traditum rectiſſimè cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur. <hi>Aug. de Pap. cont. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onat. l</hi> 4 <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>Thoſe obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations which have beene of univerſall uſe in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church, and appeare not to have beene the Conſtitutions of generall Councils, we are in reaſon to hold for Apoſtolique traditions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides theſe, wee confeſſe that there are and have been many ancient <hi>Eccleſiaſtique</hi> traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons alſo; from which, as their foundations, grew thoſe noted practiſe, of <note n="(g)" place="margin">Tert. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>not faſting</hi> on the <hi>Lords</hi> day; of <note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ib.</note> ſaying their prayers <hi>not kneeling, but ſtanding,</hi> during the whole feſtivity of <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſontide,</hi> (which in thoſe dayes continued, though in a remiſſe degree, full 50. dayes) <note n="(i)" place="margin">Juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>q. ad O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thod. Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. Apol. c. <hi>16.</hi> Baſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tu ſancto c. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>praying</hi> to God, and <hi>adoring</hi> Chriſt with their faces toward the <hi>Eaſt:</hi> 
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">Naz in l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. per. Leon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. p. <hi>423</hi> Aug. con. l. <hi>9</hi> c. <hi>13</hi>
               </note> of <hi>proſtration</hi> before the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar;</hi> of <note n="(l)" place="margin">Cyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> p. <hi>56.</hi> ad T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t at id. l. de lapſ ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</note> 
               <hi>ſigning</hi> the baptized perſon with the ſigne of the <hi>croſſe,</hi> 
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">Tert Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. mil. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>renouncing</hi> the devill, of <hi>taſting hony</hi> and <hi>milk</hi> before <hi>baptiſme;</hi> 
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">Tert. de bapt. c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> of uſing <hi>God-fathers</hi> in the baptiſmes even of <hi>children,</hi> 
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. Hiſp. l. <hi>2.</hi> de div. o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>20.</hi> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolan pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> co.</note> of <hi>exorciſing</hi> the parties to be baptized, <note n="(p)" place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al l. <hi>1.</hi> de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Aug. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</hi> de domin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a <hi>white garment</hi> upon them, which they were to weare for the ſpace of 7. or 8. dayes (from the putting off of which, the <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Eaſter</hi> was called <note n="(q)" place="margin">Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiq. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>dominica in Albis</hi>) <note n="(r)" place="margin">Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> of receiving the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4314:10"/> 
               <hi>Euchariſt faſting:</hi> 
               <note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Juſt. mar. q. ad orth. Cypr. ep. <hi>56.</hi> &amp; <hi>63.</hi>
               </note> of mixing <hi>water</hi> with the <hi>wine</hi> for the Communion; <note n="(t)" place="margin">Cypr. ibid.</note> of ſending it to ſuch as were <hi>abſent:</hi> 
               <note n="(u)" place="margin">Cypr. l. de. lapſ. num. <hi>89.</hi> Tert. l. de orat. ſub ſin. id. l. <hi>2.</hi> ad ux.</note> of <hi>eating</hi> the conſecrated bread in the <hi>Church</hi> at the <hi>time</hi> of the holy Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or carying it home to their houſes, and eating it when they thought good; <note n="(x)" place="margin">Tert. l. de Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il. c. <hi>3.</hi> id. l. <hi>2.</hi> ad ux. circa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</note> of <hi>croſsing</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves when they went out, or came in, when they aroſe or went to bed, when they ſate down to meate, when they lighted candles, and when they had any buſineſſe of moment to doe. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more <hi>cuſtoms</hi> the Church had in former times, which (doubtleſſe) moſt of them drew their <hi>breath</hi> from ſome rules and <hi>conſtitutions</hi> eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by their governours for their uſe. Now that Ceremonies and Rites of this nature are under the Churches power to ordaine, we generally <hi>grant</hi> our adverſaries; and what is granted by all ſorts of divines, cannot be called in queſtion by any, without ſome note either of ſingular <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> or <hi>arrogancy,</hi> or <hi>both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I come to ſhew the <hi>reaſon</hi> of the point,<note place="margin">
                  <p>The Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches power proved by reaſon.</p>
                  <p>No Church without Rites and rules.</p>
               </note> which may be thus declared.</p>
            <p>No Church can <hi>conſiſt</hi> without <hi>orders,</hi> no <hi>worſhip</hi> without <hi>rules, given</hi> and <hi>obſerved,</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>times, places, manner, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe (as I have ſhewed) are not of the <hi>eſſence</hi> of Gods worſhip, no more than a mans <hi>coat</hi> or <hi>skin</hi> is of the <hi>eſſence</hi> of a man; but yet ſuch neceſſary appurtenances they be, that take them away, and you take away all publique worſhip.</p>
            <p>But <hi>where</hi> are theſe orders to be found? where is this forme preſcribed? In Gods Word are <hi>no</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:4314:11"/> ſuch ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces delivered, ſome indeed are <hi>menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> were given by the <hi>Apo:</hi> to ſome particular Churches, and by them obſerved in their ſacred aſſemblies: but they were never intended to be of perpetuall <hi>right,</hi> nor for univerſall <hi>uſe;</hi> nor yet mentioned directly and <hi>purpoſely,</hi> but as the riots and diſorders of particular congregations gave them occaſion. <hi>It was not the Apoſtles drift</hi> (ſaith <note n="(a)" place="margin">Socrat. eccleſ. hiſt. l. <hi>5.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Socrates) to lay downe Canons concerning feſtivals and other ceremonies, but to become patterns of piety and godly life.</hi> Certainly the Chriſtian Churches, through all her ſucceſſions, ſhould have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly <hi>injurious</hi> to their firſt founders the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> in <hi>antiquating</hi> many of thoſe mentioned Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, had they been intended for <hi>perpetuall</hi> preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents to all Churches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Three</hi> things doe clearly <hi>evince,</hi> that neither <hi>they,</hi> nor <hi>any other</hi> forme were propounded in Scriptures to be of perpetuall right.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">No ſet forme of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed for, or u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Churches.</note>1. The <hi>impoſsibility</hi> of <hi>making</hi> ſuch orders or <hi>regiment,</hi> as ſhould <hi>fit</hi> all Churches in the world. In the time of the <hi>Law</hi> Gods people were but <hi>one,</hi> and they a <hi>ſmall</hi> people; and therefore <hi>one</hi> kinde of diſcipline might well enough ſerve their turns. But now the <hi>Church</hi> is an <hi>heterogeneall</hi> body, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of ſeverall <hi>nations,</hi> and of <hi>diſpoſitions</hi> as <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent</hi> as of <hi>countries;</hi> and therefore not to be <hi>yoked</hi> under the <hi>ſame</hi> laws and cuſtoms, <hi>Civill</hi> or <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtique.</hi> It is as hard to make one government to fit the Church in her ſeverall times and countries, as to make one <hi>ſhoo</hi> to fit <hi>all</hi> feete, or one <hi>coate</hi> to ſerve all bodies. And ſo ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi> (in effect)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4314:11"/>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Calv. Inſt. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> Sect. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chriſt would not preſcribe particular ceremonies to his Church, becauſe it was impoſsible that the ſame ceremonies ſhould be agreeable to all ſo different nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as are in the world.</hi> To the ſame purpoſe it is, which <hi>Iunius</hi> ſpeakes: <note n="(c)" place="margin">Jun. Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madan Pell. cont. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Scriptures</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>containe in them all matters of doctrine belonging ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily to faith and good life; but they only ſet downe a generall law concerning ceremonies (Let all things be done decently and in order.) Therefore particular Rites appertaining to the Church, becauſe they be mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and ambulatory, might well be omitted by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, and permitted to the conveniences of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>impoſsibility</hi> of <hi>finding</hi> out ſuch a <hi>forme,</hi> is an argument againſt it; ſuch orders could never be found in the Scriptures (at leaſt till this laſt over-weening age) never any could, or durſt <hi>determine</hi> what the <hi>Lords diſcipline</hi> (as ſome call it) is, though many, with greater <hi>paſsion</hi> than <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion,</hi> have earneſtly called for it. Certainely, had God <hi>intended</hi> ſuch a thing for his <hi>Church,</hi> or thought it neceſſary, he would have ſet it downe ſo <hi>plainly</hi> (for ſo he did the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> regiment which he meant they ſhould live by) that every <hi>Church</hi> (without groſſe ignorance) might have knowne <hi>what</hi> it was. But they are yet to learne what it is, and will be to the worlds end. Some talke of a <hi>Phoenix,</hi> and of a <hi>Philoſophers</hi> ſtone, but who did ever ſee a <hi>Phoenix?</hi> or who did ever enjoy the <hi>Philoſophers ſtone? Ab omnibus amatur, &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men virgo eſt; it hath had a great many ſuitors, but never any husband:</hi> An evident argument that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4314:12"/> theſe are but <hi>imaginary</hi> things. And ſo, that there is <hi>ſuch</hi> a diſcipline, into whoſe <hi>mold,</hi> and by whoſe <hi>modell</hi> all Churches muſt be caſt and ſquared, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that never any yet knew it, is but a meer <hi>Chimera.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The perpetuall <hi>variety</hi> of <hi>all</hi> Church-<hi>govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> doth ſufficiently diſprove it: for, if as there is one <hi>Lord,</hi> one <hi>Chriſt,</hi> one <hi>faith,</hi> and one <hi>baptiſme,</hi> ſo there be one <hi>frame</hi> of government for Chriſts Kingdome on earth, why doe not all Churches ſtick to this, as they doe to them? Scarce three Churches in the whole Chriſtian world do jump in every thing. It muſt follow therefore, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all the Churches of God are <hi>blinded,</hi> and cannot ſee what lyeth before them in broad day light; or, which is worſe, that they are all too <hi>proud</hi> to ſubmit to their <hi>maſters</hi> lawes; or, that the conceited platforme is a very <hi>Vtopian</hi> Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Two objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons removed.</note>Nor doth this argue (as ſome more fondly than truly imagine) any <hi>defect</hi> of <hi>love</hi> in <hi>God</hi> to the Church of the new Teſtament, or of <hi>fidelity</hi> in <hi>Chriſt</hi> to his Father, or of <hi>ſufficiency</hi> in the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> to direct us in our wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Want of a ſet forme argues no want of love in God.</note>1. No want of <hi>love</hi> in <hi>God</hi> to his Church <hi>now,</hi> in compariſon of the <hi>Iews,</hi> can be hence inferred: for I hope, the cleare <hi>revelation</hi> of the myſteries of ſalvation, and the abundant <hi>grace</hi> beſtowed on <hi>us</hi> above the <hi>Iews,</hi> may more truly ſhew the exube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancy of Gods affection to us in compariſon of them; than their preſcribed platforme which wee want, his care of them more than of us.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:4314:12"/>
            <p>The <hi>Philoſopher</hi> accuſed <hi>nature</hi> to be a <hi>ſtepda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> to man, and a kinde mother to other creatures, becauſe <hi>theſe</hi> bring their <hi>coats</hi> upon their backs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, and are quickly made able to ſhift for themſelves; whereas men <hi>come naked</hi> in, and are faine to depend long upon others for their ſuſtenance; A ſimple accuſation: Becauſe the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable</hi> nature, wherewith men are beautified, and their <hi>dominion</hi> over all creatures, doe much <hi>over-ballance</hi> thoſe defects, and argue more bounty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed by nature on him, than on them. And it is a cavill no leſſe ſilly, that if <hi>we</hi> be not provided for by God with a ſtanding government in the Church, as the <hi>Synagogue</hi> was, Gods care of us now is nothing ſo great, as it was at that time of them; becauſe thoſe many things wherein by Gods bounty wee <hi>out ſtrip</hi> them, are abundantly ſufficient to <hi>countervaile</hi> that defect, if it be a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. But I rather take it to be an honour to be free from ſuch a burdenſome yoke of <hi>many,</hi> and <hi>coſtly,</hi> and <hi>toilſome</hi> ceremonies, as was laid on their backs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This is no derogation, neither,<note place="margin">Nor of fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Chriſt.</note> to the <hi>fidelity</hi> of Chriſt to his Father. If we compare him with <hi>Moſes,</hi> Gods <hi>ſervant</hi> in thoſe times, <hi>Who was faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in all Gods houſe, Heb.</hi> 3.5: it is true, that hee did not all the particulars that <hi>Moſes</hi> did, and yet he was never the leſſe faithfull in his place. For the <hi>fidelity</hi> of a ſonne or ſervant, is to bee meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, not by the <hi>number</hi> of acts which he doth, but by the <hi>conformity</hi> of his actions to his fathers, or maſters commands; and ſo is our <hi>Saviours.</hi> God
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4314:13"/> appointed <hi>Moſes</hi> to make every thing belonging to that typicall and temporary diſpenſation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>pattern</hi> which he ſaw in the mount, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.5. and if he had not done ſo, hee had not been faithfull. And he ſent his Sonne to be <hi>Our high Prieſt,</hi> to ſacrifice himſelfe for the ſalvation of men; to be a <hi>Prophet</hi> alſo, to inſtruct them in all neceſſary truths; and to be a <hi>King,</hi> to protect his people in the world, and to bring them at laſt, maugre all their ſpirituall enemies, into his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious kingdome. All theſe our <hi>Lord</hi> hath truly and <hi>fully</hi> done, who will deny it? But he never gave him in charge to preſcribe <hi>externall laws</hi> for his Churches government, while warfaring here on earth.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Nor imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Scriptures.</note>3. Nor doth this involve the Scriptures <hi>imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection:</hi> for the Scripture is an <hi>inſtrument,</hi> and the perfection of an inſtrument is only <hi>relative.</hi> We doe not ſay that a <hi>pen</hi> or an <hi>axe</hi> is naught, becauſe they cannot doe all things; if a pen can write well, and an axe cut well, we take them for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and good: So, wee muſt not ſay that Gods word is <hi>inſufficient,</hi> if it reveale and <hi>preſcribe not</hi> whatſoever we imagine it ſhould: if it be able to make us <hi>wiſe to ſalvation,</hi> and <hi>compleatly furniſht to every good work</hi> (for which uſe and end only it was given, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, 17.) it muſt needs be granted that it is full and perfect, though it teach us not how the <hi>Church</hi> ſhould be governed, otherwiſe than by generall rules, theſe in my text, and ſuch other. It is with the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> as with <hi>nature; Non deficiunt in neceſſariis, nec abundant in ſuperfluis,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4314:13"/> They are neither defective in neceſſaries, nor exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive in ſuperfluous things,</hi> ſuch as this is.</p>
            <p>This paſſage I meane to cloſe up with the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of <hi>Beza,</hi> in his Epiſtle to Biſhop <hi>Grindall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bez ep. <hi>8</hi> ad Grindall ep. Lond. Proved by a Teſtimony of Beza.</note> where firſt he mentions two <hi>ſorts</hi> of men; <hi>one</hi> that would have all orders that had been of uſe in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> times, <hi>brought back</hi> into the Church, and obſerved; and whatſoever ſucceeding ages have <hi>added</hi> to them, <hi>aboliſhed:</hi> the <hi>other</hi> ſort would have <hi>old</hi> Rites of uſe in the Church <hi>after</hi> the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> times, to be retain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, as either <hi>neceſſary,</hi> or <hi>profitable,</hi> or for <hi>unities</hi> ſake: And then ſaith, <hi>Quod ad me attinet, &amp;c. As for my part, that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Apoſtles was exact and perfect I make no queſtion, but I am of another opinion concerning Rites. For, firſt it is certaine, that (the Churches eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day increaſing) the Apoſtles could not ordaine whatſoever they held expedient, and therefore in their making of orders they proceeded by degrees, as by the inſtitution of Deacons it appeares, tolerating for a while even many Iudaicall Rites, as we may ſee in the hiſtory of their Acts. Secondly, who ſeeth not, that in their externall conſtitutions they had very great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the preſent times, places, and perſons? So that it is not probable that the ſame Rites were uſed in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as is evident enough by that famous Epiſtle of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus to Victor. Beſides, ſome of their ordinances, thoſe love feaſts for example, neceſsity it ſelfe aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Therefore whatſoever was done by the Apoſtles concerning ceremonies, is not (in my conceit) either preſently or abſolutely to be made a rule. And I doe not wonder that the ancient Paſtors of the Church, (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4314:14"/> reſpect to their owne times) did antiquate ſome of thoſe firſt injunctions, and ſet up new ones in their roome. Their fault was (that by their leave I may ſpeake what I thinke) that they held not a meane in the number of their Rites, nor had ſo much regard to Chriſtian ſimplicity and purity as was meet.</hi> In this diſcourſe of his, <hi>Beza</hi> 1. <hi>delivereth</hi> his judgement plainly, that there is no <hi>forme</hi> of government left us by the <hi>Apoſtles, incompatible</hi> with additions, or detractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. 2. He <hi>proves</hi> his opinion by divers argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi rend="sup">1</hi> from its <hi>impoſsibility,</hi> the Church was <hi>then in motu, non ſtatu in motion,</hi> not in its full &amp; perfit ſtate, and they were forced to proceed by <hi>degrees</hi> in their conſtitutions, <hi>anſwerable</hi> to the <hi>increaſe</hi> of the Church, and the <hi>tempers</hi> of ſuch people as were made the Church: <hi rend="sup">2</hi> from the <hi>abrogation</hi> of <hi>Apoſtolique</hi> Rites by the Churches, as they <hi>ſaw cauſe;</hi> and of ſome of them even by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves, after they had ordained them: <hi rend="sup">3</hi> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he <hi>concludes</hi> that the <hi>faults</hi> of Church-gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, in preſcribing orders, have not ſtood in this, that they paſſed by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and ſet up their owne laws, but that they <hi>exceeded</hi> in the <hi>number</hi> or <hi>quality</hi> of ſuch Rites as they introduced into their Churches.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But perhaps it will be granted, that the <hi>Church</hi> hath power to decree ſuch <hi>Rites</hi> and ceremonies as are <hi>decent</hi> and <hi>orderly;</hi> but what if the Rites <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed</hi> doe <hi>want</hi> this externall forme and <hi>qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and are neither comely nor orderly? doth not the Church then which ordaines ſuch, <hi>exceed</hi> her commiſſion? or how ſhall we know what cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4314:14"/> are <hi>agreeable</hi> to theſe rules?</p>
            <p n="1">1. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <note place="margin">Significancie or abuſe, no mark of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decent cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</note> If any <hi>Biſhops</hi> in the Church authorize Rites not <hi>ſuitable</hi> to theſe rules, they <hi>preſume</hi> beyond their allowance, and ſhall give <hi>account</hi> to God who hath ſet them over his family the Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt <hi>not judge</hi> of ceremonies by <hi>falſe</hi> rules. <hi rend="sup">1</hi> Some <hi>reject</hi> all ceremonies as uncomely that are <hi>ſignificant;</hi> and yet thoſe <hi>holy kiſſes</hi> given and taken by the <hi>Primitive</hi> Chriſtians, were <hi>ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications</hi> of mutuall <hi>charity;</hi> the womens <hi>cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings,</hi> the mens <hi>bare heads</hi> were ſignes of womens <hi>ſubjection</hi> to their <hi>husbands,</hi> and the husbands ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone. <hi>And of ceremonies</hi> (ſaith <note n="(a)" place="margin">Pet. Mart in <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>11.</hi> vid. etiam Calv. Inſt. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> Sect. <hi>15</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Peter Martyr) thoſe are the moſt laudable, that are the moſt lively in ſignification.</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">2</hi> Some againe condemne <hi>all</hi> Rites that are or have been <hi>uſed</hi> by the <hi>Romane</hi> Church; when yet it is moſt certain, that not only <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but <hi>Pagans</hi> too, by the light of <hi>reaſon,</hi> may be <hi>competent</hi> judges of decency and order in externall Rites. <hi rend="sup">3</hi> Others will allow this ſurname to none that have been <hi>abuſed</hi> to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and Idolatry; but would have them all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed as moſt uncomely for the ſervice of God, but without reaſon; may not Churches be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted fit places for publike worſhip, becauſe they have formerly been polluted with Idolatry? may not that body which hath made it ſelfe a member of an harlot, become a glorious member of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and a holy Temple for Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to dwell in? Wiſe men have alwayes thought, that the ſeparation of the uſe of a thing from its abuſe, is very <hi>poſsible,</hi> and that the <hi>uſe</hi> of ſome
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4314:15"/> things ſtript out of their abuſes, is very <hi>commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> To take away the uſe of a Ceremony becauſe formerly abuſed, <hi>Curatio quidem eſt, ſed curatio carniſicis, non medici,</hi> (ſaith <note n="(b)" place="margin">Caſſand. Commonſtr. viae, Circ. med.</note> 
               <hi>Caſſander</hi> rightly) <hi>is a cure of the abuſe indeed, but the cure of a hangman,</hi> who takes away diſeaſes, diſaſters, and life and all at a clap, <hi>not of a phyſician,</hi> who ſo expells the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, as he ſaves the life.</p>
            <p>Theſe are all falſe <hi>Cards</hi> to ſaile by. By the beſt writers <hi>ceremonies</hi> are then judged to be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable</hi> to theſe directions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When they are not <hi>elevated</hi> above their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, neither uſed as true and proper <hi>acts</hi> of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, (as <hi>vowed</hi> chaſtity, poverty, and regular o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience among the Papiſts are,) nor as <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> to produce ſupernaturall effects, as <hi>holy wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> is ſprinkled in the Church of Rome to waſh away <hi>veniall</hi> ſinnes, and the ſigne of the <hi>Croſſe</hi> is uſed to <hi>drive away devils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. When for their <hi>multitude</hi> they be neither <hi>burdenſome</hi> to the Church, making <hi>Iews</hi> of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Goſpell;</hi> nor <hi>occaſions</hi> of <hi>diverting</hi> their affections and thoughts from ſuch religious acts and ſervices as are <hi>ſubſtantiall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore ſuch Rites as are not oppoſite to theſe rules, we are to hold for decent and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy belongs to Superiours.</note>3. The <hi>determination</hi> of this decency belongs not to <hi>private</hi> perſons; it is not for them to <hi>nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> and governours to <hi>chuſe,</hi> or for them to bring the <hi>writing,</hi> and ſuperiours to give the <hi>ſeale;</hi> this would be to make authority but a meere cypher,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4314:15"/> and the Biſhops of the Church like thoſe <hi>images</hi> in the Pſalme, <hi>Which have eyes and ſee not, hands and handle not, &amp;c.</hi> this were an utter <hi>vverturning</hi> of the body, a placing of the feete where the head ſhould be. But our Rulers muſt be judges in theſe matters, the <hi>Kings</hi> majeſty the <hi>ſupreme,</hi> and the <hi>Prelates</hi> of the Church the <hi>ſubordinate;</hi> for 1. this is the <hi>honour</hi> belonging to their places, as it is the honour of the head to judge what is fit and comely and conducible to the wel-fare of the body. 2. they are <hi>beſt fitted</hi> for this work of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining, both in reſpect of their <hi>learning</hi> and <hi>experience,</hi> and becauſe of that <hi>divine aſsiſtance,</hi> which by their <hi>maſters</hi> owne promiſe (<hi>Loe I am with you to the end of the world, Mat.</hi> 28.20.) is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally afforded them, though not ſo far as to ſecure them from all <hi>poſsibility</hi> of <hi>miſtaking</hi> in their deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. To their ſentence in theſe things muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours ſubmit, if not their <hi>judgements</hi> (for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they are not bound to beleeve at all times that they doe all things well) yet their <hi>practiſes,</hi> both for the honour that is due to their places, and the peace of Gods Church which every good member will purſue. In <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8, 9, 10, 11, 12. <hi>God enjoyneth</hi> the people under the <hi>paine</hi> of death in all their doubts and controverſies to <hi>ſtand</hi> to the ſentence of the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and to ſquare their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes thereby: he thought it not fit <hi>then</hi> for the people to be judges of doubtfull caſes, and doth he think it convenient <hi>now?</hi> I will therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the ſpeech of <hi>Nazianzene.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Naz in Orat. quâ ſe purgat.</note> 
               <hi>Preſume not ye that are ſheep, to make your ſelves guides of them
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4314:16"/> that ſhould guide you, neither ſeek to skip over the fold which they have pitcht about you, it ſufficeth for your part, if you give your ſelves to be ordered. Take not upon you to judge, nor make them ſubject to your laws, who ſhould be a law to you; for God is not a God of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, but of order and peace in all the Churches of the Saints,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33.</p>
            <p>And ſo <hi>leaving</hi> Rites and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> for their determination, to the <hi>heads</hi> of the Church, as peeces of <hi>coine</hi> which beare their image and <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription;</hi> I paſſe from the <hi>point</hi> to the <hi>Conſectaries</hi> reſulting from it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From hence we may ſee, that <hi>Laws or Canons concerning orders in the Church, are alterable, and binde to their uſe no longer than they that made them are pleaſed to urge them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Matters of <hi>faith</hi> and morality will endure no addition, diminution or change, becauſe their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is <hi>divine;</hi> but matters of <hi>order</hi> and decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy doe, becauſe their authority is <hi>humane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Every particular, or nationall Church hath power to ordaine, change, and aboliſh ceremonies and Rites or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained only by mans authority, ſo as all things be done to edification.</hi> 
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Art.</hi> 14.</note> It is the ſubſcribed doctrine of our owne Church, and a proofe of the Conſecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Upon this ground S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his owne Church <hi>abrogated</hi> an <hi>old cuſtome</hi> of feaſting at the <hi>Tombs</hi> of <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtyrs</hi> 
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ud. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es in Aug de Civ. Dei. l.</hi> 8 <hi>c</hi> 27. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, ne u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſio l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſis ſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> andi, &amp; q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ua illa qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi parent l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> leſt occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of quaffing ſhould be given thereby to drunkards, and becauſe thoſe <hi>parentalia, funerall feaſts</hi> were very like to <hi>heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> ſuperſtition. And how many <hi>Apoſtolique</hi> and <hi>ancient</hi> Rites have long ſince bidden the world
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4314:16"/> 
               <hi>good-night</hi> by the Churches <hi>pleaſure</hi> only, on the ſame ground? <note n="(c)" place="margin">Caſſand. l de oſſic. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pag. <hi>855.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Caſſander</hi> reckons up <hi>two ſorts</hi> of <hi>old</hi> ceremonies; which becauſe they were dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, have been differently dealt with.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some there were, which are of <hi>perpetuall uſe</hi> to preſerve the memory of Chriſts benefits, and to traine up Chriſtian people in piety. Such were thoſe famous feſtivals of <hi>Eaſter, Aſcenſion,</hi> and <hi>Whitſontide;</hi> for by their <hi>anniverſary</hi> ſolemnizati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, and by the publique <hi>reading</hi> and explaining the hiſtories <hi>ſutable</hi> to thoſe holy-dayes, people are put in minde of thoſe <hi>Acts</hi> which Chriſt did for their <hi>redemption,</hi> and excited to ſhew their thankfulneſſe to him by their love and obedience to his laws. Of this ſort alſo have <hi>ſinging</hi> of Pſalms, and ſacred hymnes in the Church, reading of <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table prayers</hi> and Scriptures at the holy <hi>communion, ſilence of women</hi> in the congregation, and the <hi>faſt of Lent</hi> been accounted. All theſe therefore have been religiouſly preſerved without the leaſt alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others of them were of an <hi>inferiour</hi> nature, and may be divided into <hi>three</hi> ranks.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Rites of no great <hi>moment</hi> for their matter or uſe; as their <hi>holy kiſſes, ſtanding while</hi> they pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed on the Lords day, the <hi>taſting of hony</hi> and milk by the perſons to be baptiſed, <hi>ad infantiae ſignifi cationem, to ſignifie their infancy in Chriſt,</hi> as S. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> ſaith, alluding to that ſpeech of S. <hi>Peter, As new borne babes deſire the ſincere milk of Gods word, that ye may grow thereby.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Rites of very <hi>good uſe, while</hi> their <hi>equity</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4314:17"/> but yet <hi>fitted</hi> only to the <hi>preſent</hi> times. Such an one was the <hi>abſtinence</hi> from <hi>Idolothytes, things ſtrangled,</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi> impoſed on the <hi>Gentiles</hi> by <hi>Apoſtolique</hi> authority, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. For this as it was <hi>enjoyned</hi> only in <hi>favour</hi> of the <hi>peeviſh</hi> Jews, who counted ſome meats uncleane, and were kept off from Chriſt becauſe thoſe abominable meats (as they thought them to be) were eaten by the Chriſtians; ſo it was to <hi>live no longer</hi> than the <hi>ſcandall</hi> continued. Of this nature was the <hi>cuſtome</hi> of baptiſing people that were to be entred into the Church, at the <hi>two</hi> great feſtivals of <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſontide</hi> only: (except in caſe of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent neceſſity) and in the <hi>mother Churches</hi> of their ſeverall countries, and no where elſe. This order was a very good one during thoſe times, both in reſpect of that <hi>Sacrament,</hi> which hereby became the more reverend and ſacred; and of the <hi>perſons</hi> to be baptized, who had liberty by this, to <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare</hi> the better for their <hi>journies</hi> to thoſe mother Churches (which ſometimes were very far from their dwellings) and to get themſelves ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>catechized</hi> in the Chriſtian religion, that they might be able to give an account of their faith, before they received their baptiſme. Nor was this cuſtome <hi>prejudiciall</hi> to any of them, becauſe being for the moſt part men and women, they were not <hi>ſubject</hi> to ſudden death, as tender <hi>infants</hi> are, and if by ſickneſſe or any caſualty they were brought into danger of death, they found the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> to be baptized. But the equity of this cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome continued no longer than the converſion
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4314:17"/> of <hi>Gentiles</hi> laſted; and therefore, <hi>extincta gentili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate,</hi> when <hi>Paganiſme</hi> was almoſt ſwallowed up of Chriſtianity, and the <hi>only</hi> perſons to receive this <hi>badge,</hi> were <hi>children</hi> borne in the Church, who by reaſon of their tender infant age, were <hi>uncapable</hi> of inſtruction, and <hi>ſubject</hi> to manifold deaths and dangers, and ſo might frequently have ended <hi>this</hi> life before they had received the Sacrament of <hi>another</hi> life, (ſhould they have <hi>been deferred</hi> and put over to thoſe <hi>two</hi> times) this order <hi>began</hi> to expire.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third ſort, were ſuch Rites as were <hi>chaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> uſed at their firſt inſtitution, but afterward, by the licentiouſneſſe of people, did ſeeme to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with <hi>inſeparable abuſes;</hi> of this ſort were thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> mentioned <hi>Iude</hi> 12. <hi>feaſts of charity;</hi> and thoſe <hi>meetings together in the night,</hi> which they called <hi>vigills,</hi> becauſe they were wont to <hi>watch</hi> together in prayer even till <hi>midnight,</hi> (eſpecially in the night before <hi>Eaſter.</hi>) All theſe the <hi>Church</hi> hath <hi>aboliſhed,</hi> though in a <hi>different</hi> way. Some were <hi>ſuddenly</hi> and in an inſtant remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as the <hi>uſe of pictures</hi> in the Church, by the <note n="a" place="margin">Elibert. Counc.</note> 
               <hi>Elibertine</hi> councill, <hi>Ne quod colitur, in parieti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus depingeretur, that that which was to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, might not be painted upon walls:</hi> and the <hi>three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold dipping</hi> by the fourth <hi>Toletane</hi> councill, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe abuſed by the <hi>Arrians, Conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tolet.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 5. others were ſuffered like old buildings to run to ruine by <hi>degrees,</hi> till they fell of themſelves. Some ſhe hath clean <hi>caſhiered;</hi> others ſhe hath only <hi>chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> into ſomewhat elſe not unlike them, as <hi>vigills</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:4314:18"/> into <hi>faſting</hi> dayes, and <hi>live feaſts</hi> into <hi>collections</hi> for the poore. Now, though the <hi>cauſes</hi> why theſe have been abrogated, were particular, yet the <hi>ground</hi> on which the <hi>Church</hi> did it, and by which ſhe muſt be juſtified in ſo doing, was the <hi>nature</hi> and quality of thoſe Rites, being all <hi>humane</hi> conſtitutions; and her <hi>authority</hi> over things of that nature, either to <hi>make</hi> or <hi>marre,</hi> as occaſion ſerveth; for the <hi>hand</hi> that gives them <hi>life,</hi> may <hi>ſtrike them dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor may the <hi>Church</hi> only alter and <hi>aboliſh old</hi> ceremonies, but <hi>adde new,</hi> either for the <hi>begetting</hi> of an honourable reſpect to Gods ordinances, or the <hi>ſtirring</hi> up of our dead <hi>devotions</hi> in his ſervice. <note n="(b)" place="margin">So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. eccl. hiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Socrates</hi> tells us, that the cuſtome of ſinging <hi>Anthems</hi> in the Church, was brought in by S. <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Antioch;</hi> becauſe having heard ſome <hi>Angels</hi> in a <hi>viſion</hi> chanting out the praiſes of God with <hi>interchangeable</hi> notes, hee thought it would be a good exerciſe for Gods <hi>earthly Angels</hi> in their <hi>publique</hi> aſſemblies, which are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a heaven on earth.</hi> And S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> becauſe hee made account that <hi>ſinging</hi> had no ſmall <hi>efficacy</hi> in it <hi>ad commovendum ad pictatem animum,</hi> to move the minde to godlineſſe, (ſaith S <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug ep.</hi> 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9</note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> in one place) and leſt the people being heavily afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>Arrian</hi> perſecution, <hi>Moeroris tadio contabeſceret, ſhould pine away with too much ſorow,</hi> (ſaith the ſame <hi>Father</hi> in another <note n="(d)" place="margin">Aug conſeſ. l. <hi>9</hi> c <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> place) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <hi>ſinging</hi> to be uſed in the Oh: of <hi>Milan.</hi> And from theſe two Biſhops drew that <hi>cuſtome</hi> of <hi>ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in the <hi>Eaſterne</hi> and <hi>Weſterne</hi> Churches its <hi>origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:4314:18"/>
            <p>What was <hi>Ignatius</hi> and S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> if we look at their authority, more than other <hi>Biſhops</hi> of the Church? that liberty therefore which they had, to <hi>make new</hi> orders, when they ſaw cauſe, have all other <hi>Prelates</hi> in their Churches, ſo far as the <hi>laws</hi> of the <hi>lands</hi> in which they are, will permit.</p>
            <p>It is an <hi>envious</hi> outcry therefore which is made among us, that <hi>Popery</hi> is comming in,<note place="margin">Alteration of ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies no argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery.</note> and Gods <hi>true</hi> religion going out, becauſe ſome <hi>ſeeming al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations</hi> are made in our <hi>ceremonies,</hi> and ſome <hi>new</hi> ones are, by the <hi>examples</hi> of <hi>Superiours commended</hi> to our uſe; or rather, ſome ancient cuſtomes, which have been <hi>continued</hi> in our <hi>mother</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>revived</hi> in others. A <hi>heavy charge</hi> it is, and had need be well <hi>proved</hi> by them that thus cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, or elſe it is a <hi>foule ſlander,</hi> and ſo indeed it is. For what are ceremonies to doctrine? What is the uſe of the Churches <hi>liberty</hi> in <hi>theſe</hi> things, to <hi>Popery?</hi> May not the <hi>apparrell</hi> alter, and the <hi>body</hi> remaine the ſame? May not <hi>ceremonies,</hi> which are the <hi>clothing</hi> of the Spouſe, admit ſome <hi>changes,</hi> and the <hi>doctrine</hi> remaine inviolate? Muſt <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi> needs peep in, becauſe our <hi>Biſhops</hi> doe uſe the liberty which they ever had?</p>
            <p>A rumour it is, that argues either <hi>ignorance,</hi> or <hi>envy,</hi> or <hi>vain-glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſome, perhaps, but <hi>ignorance.</hi> 1. Of the <hi>diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> between <hi>ſubſtance</hi> and <hi>ceremony</hi> doctrine and diſcipline. 2. Of the <hi>Churches power</hi> to adde, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, and make a change in theſe things, if cauſe be offered. And I would wiſh all ſuch to labour to be better inſtructed, and till they be, to hold
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4314:19"/> their peace, and neither trouble themſelves, nor others with things they underſtand not.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Envy,</hi> I am afraid, and ill-affectedneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thoſe that are <hi>above</hi> them in the <hi>Church,</hi> is the cauſe of this outcry in too many; becauſe their <hi>eyes</hi> are too <hi>weak</hi> to look upon the luſtre of thoſe <hi>Stars</hi> in the Church, or their <hi>wills untaught</hi> to <hi>keep</hi> their <hi>laws,</hi> or <hi>beare</hi> their <hi>cenſures,</hi> therefore they <hi>dart</hi> their bitter and <hi>biting</hi> words upon them, like thoſe <hi>Salvages,</hi> who ſhoot their arrows at the <hi>Sun,</hi> becauſe he ſcorcheth them with his beams.</p>
            <p>Let ſuch take heed, leſt while they reſemble the <hi>devill</hi> in his <hi>ſinne,</hi> and maligne the happineſſe of others, they be not made like him in <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and loſe their owne.</p>
            <p>If this envious <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> be no cauſe, yet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>vainglory,</hi> with which too many are inebriated, may <hi>occaſion</hi> theſe uncharitable reports; <hi>Abſalons</hi> ambitious traducing of his fathers bleſſed govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to advance his owne, doth plainly enough ſhew, that the <hi>ſlandering</hi> of governours for the getting of a <hi>private name,</hi> is a trick and peece of artifice as old at leaſt as <hi>Abſalon.</hi> Who ſees not, that this is a ready way for men to get a <hi>great opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> among the people? either of ſingular <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> that they are able to diſcerne <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in his <hi>ſwadling</hi> clouts, and deſcry him, while he is but putting in his head at the doore; or of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable zeale and piety, that they are ſuch as cannot behold the declining of the Goſpels purity, and the ſad approach of ſuperſtition, without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints and outcryes.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:4314:19"/>
            <p>But let me tell them: 1. That this <hi>odious ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour</hi> having no ſufficient ground to ſtand upon, is but a <hi>ſlander;</hi> and which is worſe, <hi>Scandalum magnatum, a blaſpheming of dignities,</hi> a ſin, which S. <hi>Peter</hi> attributeth to notorious preſumption, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>they tremble not to ſpeak evill of dignities:</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10. 2. That a <hi>ſlander</hi> is not the right <hi>way</hi> to true <hi>honour;</hi> never was true zeale kindled at a <hi>kitchin</hi> fire, nor ever ſweet name built on the ruine of a private mans, much leſſe of a whole governments reputation. Once <hi>Heroſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> ſet fire on the <hi>glory</hi> of the world for a building, <hi>Diana's</hi> magnificent <hi>Temple,</hi> to get a <hi>name:</hi> and a name he hath gotten; but what name? a name of <hi>obloquy</hi> and diſgrace to the worlds end. And ſuch a name (I beleeve) wil be the portion of all thoſe, <hi>Qui ex incenſo Dei Templo gloriam quaerunt</hi> (as <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> ſpeakes) who ſeek their owne glory by ſuch <hi>ſeditious</hi> and <hi>incendiary</hi> ſlanders.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the ſecond Conſectary.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Conſectary</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Churches are not tyed to the ſame orders:</hi> Each Church hath her liberty, either to <hi>take</hi> ſuch as are made ready to her hand by others, or to <hi>make</hi> new Canons of her owne for the government of her people. And ſo our <hi>Church</hi> teacheth us to judge in her 34. <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Art.</hi> 34.</note> 
               <hi>Article. It is not neceſſary</hi> (ſaith the Article) <hi>that ceremonies and traditions be in all places one, or altogether alike: for at all times they have been divers; and may be changed according to the diverſities of countries, times and maners. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Rites and ceremonies</hi> (ſaith <note n="(b)" place="margin">Zanch. de Red l. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>764.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Zanchy) are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted for the edification of the Church, it is manifeſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4314:20"/> that in theſe things liberty is to be left to Churches, that every Church may ſo cary her ſelfe in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as ſhe thinkes beſt for the good of her beleevers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On theſe concluſions of our <hi>owne Church,</hi> and that learned writer, <note n="(a)" place="margin">Socr. l. <hi>5.</hi> eccl. hiſt. c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Socrates</hi> may ſerve for a <hi>comment,</hi> for he reckons up many <hi>ſeverall</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, all enjoying their <hi>ſeverall</hi> orders.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Greek</hi> Church gave the Communion in <hi>leavened bread,</hi> the <hi>Latines</hi> in <hi>unleavened:</hi> the <hi>Greeks</hi> kept their <hi>Eaſter, quartâ decimâ lunâ,</hi> on the <hi>fourteenth day</hi> of that moneth <hi>exactly,</hi> fall when it would; but the <hi>Latins</hi> alwayes on the <hi>firſt day of the week,</hi> the reſurrection day. In <hi>Rome</hi> they <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted</hi> on <hi>Saturdaies,</hi> in <hi>Milan</hi> not ſo: in <hi>Rome</hi> their <hi>Lent</hi> was wont to begin but <hi>three</hi> weeks <hi>before Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> in <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Illyrium, ſixe</hi> weeks, and in <hi>other</hi> Churches <hi>ſeven.</hi> Among the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches, their faſting was a <hi>totall</hi> forbearing of all kinde of food till <hi>Sun ſet;</hi> but in ſome <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches, it ſtood onely in <hi>delectu ciborum,</hi> in abſtinence from <hi>fleſh</hi> only, and brake up at <hi>three</hi> firſt, then at <hi>twelve</hi> a clock. In <hi>Antioch</hi> the <hi>altar</hi> ſtood in the <hi>Weſt</hi> part of the Church, in <hi>others</hi> alwayes in the <hi>Eaſt.</hi> In <hi>Hellas, Ieruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Theſſaly,</hi> and among the <hi>Novatians</hi> alſo at <hi>Conſtantinople, Evening pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> was read by <hi>candle light;</hi> and S. <note n="(b)" place="margin">Hier. ep. ad vigilant.</note> 
               <hi>Hierome</hi> gives the reaſon, <hi>Non ad fugandas tenebras, ſed ad ſignum laetitiae demonſtrandum, not to drive away darkneſſe,</hi> (for at thoſe houres it was light enough) <hi>but to repreſent the ſpirituall rejoycing of Chriſtians:</hi> but in <hi>other</hi> Churches it was read by <hi>day light.</hi> At <hi>Alexandria</hi> they admitted <hi>Catechumeniſts</hi> to the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4314:20"/> office of <hi>reading,</hi> and <hi>expounding</hi> the Scriptures in the Church; in <hi>other</hi> places none were appointed to thoſe functions, <hi>till</hi> they were <hi>baptized.</hi> In ſome <hi>Churches</hi> the <hi>Communion</hi> was celebrated <hi>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> Sunday, in <hi>others,</hi> not <hi>ſo often.</hi> Among <hi>ſome</hi> people, it was given to <hi>children,</hi> as well as to men and women, (as S. <note n="(c)" place="margin">Cypr. de lap. num. <hi>89.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> tells us) and <note n="(d)" place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. <hi>107.</hi> ad Vitalem.</note> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, that there was ſuch a cuſtome in his time: but this was not the maner of other Churches, as <note n="(e)" place="margin">Pam. in loc. cit. Cypriani.</note> 
               <hi>Pamelius</hi> obſerves in theſe words. <hi>Quia apud alios authores rariſsima fit illius mentio, &amp;c. becauſe there is but little mention made of that cuſtome in other authors, therefore I ſuſpect that it was neither univerſall, nor of any long continuance after S. Auſtins time.</hi> In the <hi>African</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches for a great while together, they never gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Churches peace</hi> to ſuch as fell into the <hi>cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina majora,</hi> the <hi>fouler</hi> ſort of <hi>crimes</hi> after <hi>baptiſm;</hi> but in <hi>other</hi> Churches they were <hi>more indulgent</hi> to offenders upon their true repentance, as <note n="(f)" place="margin">Petav. in Epiphan.</note> 
               <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavius</hi> hath noted.</p>
            <p>We ſee by theſe examples that <hi>great</hi> was the <hi>variety</hi> of Church-cuſtoms and conſtitutions. And yet for all this diverſity, the Churches held the <hi>unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace;</hi> none of them being either ſo <hi>proud</hi> as to preſcribe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, nor ſo <hi>uncharitable,</hi> as to wrangle among themſelves about thoſe differences. Only once <note n="(g)" place="margin">Euſeb.</note> 
               <hi>Victor</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> preſumed to excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate all <hi>Aſia</hi> for <hi>differing</hi> from the <hi>Latins</hi> in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving <hi>Eaſter.</hi> But <hi>Irenaeus of Lions in France,</hi> in the name of his fellow Biſhops, did ſharply <hi>rebuke</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:4314:21"/> him for it; alledging againſt him the <hi>examples</hi> of former Biſhops, and in particular of <hi>Polycarpus</hi> of <hi>Smyrua,</hi> and <hi>Anicetus</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they differed in this obſervation, yet they held a friendly communion together.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Calv. ep. <hi>18</hi> ad Farel.</note> 
               <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> tells <hi>Farell,</hi> that as for <hi>himſelfe,</hi> he was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what <hi>ſparing</hi> of ceremonies, <hi>Luther liberall, Bucer indifferent;</hi> yet they all maintained very good <hi>correſpondency,</hi> and judged thoſe differences in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Rites to be no juſt cauſe why they ſhould breake amity. And indeed they are not, no more than difference in apparell is a good reaſon why the children of the ſame father ſhould maintaine a contention. <hi>Diſſonantia jejunii fidei conſonanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am non tollit; difference in faſting</hi> (ſaith <hi>Irenaeus) takes not away agreement in faith:</hi> and, <hi>In una fide ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil officit eccleſiae ſanctae conſuetudo diverſa,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Gregory;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Outlandiſh Church-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders no rule to us.</note> 
               <hi>Different Church cuſtoms bring no preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to their one moſt holy faith.</hi> Nay it is good (ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin) that there ſhould be this variety, for this is that raiment of needle-work wherewith the Kings daughter is clothed and beautified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With what warrant then doth <hi>Cartwright</hi> or any of his followers, ſtrive to bring us to <hi>out-lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh</hi> cuſtoms, and make a <hi>ſchiſme from us,</hi> or a <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction among us,</hi> for <hi>maintaining</hi> the liberty where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Chriſt hath honoured us, of making and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by our owne rules? <hi>Graviter peccant &amp;c. They are guilty of a great fault</hi> 
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zanch. l. de Red. p.</hi> 765. Graviter pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, qui prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter has indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias turbant ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſias, dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant alios prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes &amp; magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus: haec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine pietas quam jacta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus? haecci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e charitas, quam debemus eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s &amp; fractibus?</note> (ſaith <hi>Zanchy) who for theſe indifferent ceremonies doe diſturb the Churches, and damne all other magiſtrates and rulers, becauſe they uſe their liberty in theſe things: is this
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4314:21"/> the piety which is boaſted of? is this the charity which we owe to the Churches of God?</hi> If they want piety and charity, who trouble and conteſt with <hi>other</hi> Churches about ceremonies, much more doe <hi>they</hi> lack it, who in this quarrell trouble the quiet of their <hi>owne,</hi> becauſe ſhe will not proſtrate her ſelfe before their <hi>Idoll,</hi> and be <hi>ſervant</hi> to their humors. <hi>Came the word of God from them, or came it to them only?</hi> (that I may ſpeak in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> language, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.36.) Are they the <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to whom the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars</hi> muſt bow? all Churches muſt <hi>ſtrike</hi> ſail? <hi>Calvin</hi> indeed was too highly conceited of his owne invented diſcipline (as <hi>Pigmalion</hi> of his image) and having made it, did give too honourable a ſtyle to it: but did his friends ſo mightily eſteem it? <note n="(a)" place="margin">Vide Calv. ep. ad Pullinger. It. ep. ad Tigur. miniſt. It. ep. Bullinger. ad Calvin.</note> Was it not <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed</hi> by his <hi>owne</hi> Senate and Citizens? was not he glad for the upholding of it to <hi>beg</hi> the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of <hi>Bazil, Zurich,</hi> and other <hi>Helvetian</hi> Churches? And when (to gratifie him) they gave it a teſtimony, was not this the <hi>greateſt</hi> praiſe they could afford it, that thoſe <hi>conſiſtoricall</hi> laws of his were <hi>good</hi> ones, and ſuch as were <hi>agreeable</hi> to the word of God, and might well be <hi>tolerated:</hi> not ſuch as were of <hi>neceſsity</hi> to be received into their or other Churches? To goe no further than <hi>Beza, Calvins</hi> inward friend and ſcholar; <note n="(b)" place="margin">Bez. in vit. Calvin.</note> He in the life of <hi>Calvin,</hi> ſpeaking of the <hi>cauſe</hi> why <hi>Calvin</hi> did ſo earneſtly <hi>contend</hi> for the continuance of it, ſaith, it was, <hi>Quod eam urbem videret his fraenis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digere, becauſe he ſaw that that City</hi> (being then it ſeems ſomewhat licentious) <hi>had need of ſuch a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4314:22"/> bridle;</hi> by which we ſee, that he derived not its pedegree as high as heaven, nor <hi>maintained</hi> it to be the <hi>Lords</hi> diſcipline, nor <hi>preſcribed</hi> it <hi>imperiouſly</hi> to other Churches. Nor doe her owne <hi>divines</hi> eſteem it <hi>The government:</hi> for when occaſions have brought them among us, they have with <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular reſpect</hi> conformed and <hi>ſubmitted</hi> themſelves in practiſe to <hi>our</hi> received orders. Herein obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> rule which he gives in one of his <hi>Epiſtles.</hi> 
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Aug. ep. <hi>118.</hi> ad Januar.</note> 
               <hi>Quod ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> contra fidem, &amp;c. That con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution which is neither againſt faith or good maners, is to be reckoned of, as in it ſelfe indifferent, and to bee obſerved according to the company with whom we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe.</hi> And againe, <hi>Ad quam cun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, &amp;c. To what Church ſoever thou ſhalt come, follow their cuſtoms, if thou meaneſt neither to give nor take offence.</hi> Herein alſo imitating S. <hi>Pauls</hi> example, who became <hi>all things to all men,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.20. and that of S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> 
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Aug. ep. ad Caſulan.</note> who though in his owne Church of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> he kept no <hi>Saturday</hi> faſt, yet when he came to <hi>Rome,</hi> where it was the cuſtome, hee <hi>faſted</hi> as <hi>they</hi> did; by that demeanour giving occaſion to that proverb which hath been long in uſe. <hi>Si fueris Romae, Romano vivito more, if you come to Rome, live as Romans doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our owne men are only they, our <hi>Engliſh</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts are the greateſt admirers of <hi>Rome</hi> and the <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall</hi> power, becauſe they live a <hi>great way</hi> from them, and know them only in <hi>imagination</hi> (which too often like a <hi>falſe</hi> glaſſe, is a deceitfull repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter) ſo are our owne <hi>diſciplinarians</hi> the onely men, that do ſo much adore that <hi>Geneva platform,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:4314:22"/> becauſe they never had any practicall knowledge and experience of it. And it is the <hi>unhappy</hi> chance of our Church to have her <hi>bowells eaten</hi> out by her <hi>owne</hi> children whom ſhe hath caried in her <hi>womb,</hi> nurſed at her <hi>breaſts,</hi> and <hi>fed</hi> with her favours and preferments.</p>
            <p>A deſtiny too bad for a <hi>well-reformed,</hi> nay (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice to other Churches be it ſpoken) the <hi>beſt reformed</hi> Church in the world; a <hi>Church</hi> (I appeale to all <hi>Church-ſtories</hi>) which in her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and government commeth neereſt the <hi>pattern</hi> of pious and reverend <hi>Antiquity.</hi> A go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſo <hi>moderate,</hi> and full of <hi>reſpect</hi> to thoſe <hi>elder</hi> Saints (who were in <hi>Chriſt</hi> before us, and are now <hi>triumphing</hi> in heaven, while we are <hi>militant</hi> yet on earth, and fighting for our <hi>Crown</hi>) <note n="(a)" place="margin">Confer. ad Hampt. Court. pag. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> that a <hi>French Embaſſadour</hi> in the beginning of our laſt <hi>Kings</hi> raigne of bleſſed memory, upon the <hi>view</hi> of our ſolemne ſervice &amp; <hi>ceremonies</hi> at <hi>Canterbury</hi> and at <hi>Court,</hi> gave out; That <hi>if the reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in France had kept the ſame orders among them that we have, he was aſſured there would have been in that countrey many thouſand Proteſtants at that time, more than there were.</hi> But alas poore mother, it is thy <hi>lot</hi> to be deſpiſed by thine <hi>owne</hi> ſons, and if there be no remedy, thou muſt beare it; <hi>Time and chance</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) happeneth to all men,</hi> and ſo it doth to all <hi>Churches,</hi> 
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hor. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Carm. Ode</hi> 24. Levius ſit pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia, quicquid corrigere eſt nefas.</note> 
               <hi>Patience is a means to make that burden eaſie, which muſt be endured with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remedy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the <hi>third</hi> Conſectary.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:4314:23"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Conſectary</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Perſons that ſpurne at Church-ordinances, may be juſtly puniſhed by Church-governours:</hi> their power to <hi>make</hi> orders <hi>implies</hi> a power to <hi>cenſure</hi> diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in whomſoever they finde refractary. For, every law <hi>ſuppoſeth</hi> in the Law-maker, a power <hi>directive</hi> to make it, and a power <hi>coercive</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain tranſgreſſors of it; as S. <hi>Paul</hi> implies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. where (ſpeaking of the Magiſtrate) he ſaith, <hi>He beareth not the ſword in vaine.</hi> Firſt, he <hi>beareth a ſword,</hi> hath authority to <hi>puniſh</hi> as well as to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe. Secondly, he beareth it not in <hi>vain,</hi> hath authority to ſmite with that ſword, and to put his power in <hi>practiſe</hi> upon evill doers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is one Law giver</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Iames, cap.</hi> 4.12.) <hi>who is able to ſave and to deſtroy:</hi> in which words is given us by conſequent to underſtand, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to all Law-givers to doe either of theſe, as occaſion requires.</p>
            <p>And the reaſon why they are to have <hi>this</hi> pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er as well as the former, is, becauſe it is a <hi>back</hi> to the former; without this that other would be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable; for <note n="(c)" place="margin">Morinus de cenſ. eccleſ. c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Inermis authoritas, non authoritas dicenda eſt, ſed authoritatis larva: unarmed authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is rather a mask and ſemblance of authority, than au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Into all creatures God hath put <hi>two</hi> faculties.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A <hi>concupiſcible,</hi> by which they are caryed to <hi>ſeek out</hi> whatſoever things are needfull for their preſervation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An <hi>Iraſcible,</hi> by which they are <hi>inabled ad omnia contraria eliminanda,</hi> to <hi>expell</hi> by <hi>ſlight</hi> or <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance,</hi> at leaſt in endeavour, whatſoever threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4314:23"/> their <hi>deſtruction.</hi> And without this laſt the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> would not be ſufficient to keep the creature in being. Anſwerable to this, there is in <hi>governours</hi> a <hi>concupiſcible</hi> faculty of <hi>making</hi> good orders for the <hi>maintenance</hi> of that body, wherof themſelves are a part: and an <hi>Iraſcible,</hi> of <hi>reſiſting</hi> and <hi>executing</hi> ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on ſuch irregular perſons, men of <hi>Belial,</hi> as aſſault that body, thoſe orders; and without this that other of making laws, is not only <hi>weak</hi> and of little uſe, but oft times a <hi>ſnare</hi> to law-makers, who otherwiſe would be (like the log in the <hi>fable) fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula vulgi,</hi> a <hi>ſcorne</hi> to the rude, unruly <hi>multitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leſt ſome may think, that this <hi>laſt</hi> power is peculiar to the <hi>civill</hi> magiſtrate,<note place="margin">A coactive power neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Chu: governours.</note> and belongs not to Biſhops and governours of the Church; their <hi>Canons</hi> being but <hi>councells,</hi> and their <hi>authority</hi> only to <hi>perſwade;</hi> as <note n="(a)" place="margin">V. d. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin. catech.</note> ſome of <hi>note,</hi> to the diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their learning, doe not ſtick to ſay:<note place="margin">Par. Orat. de Q. anleges magiſt. obligent Conſc. pag. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> Caſt your eyes on <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> two <hi>Biſhops</hi> of the Church. S. <hi>Paul</hi> armeth them both with this <hi>dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> authority. <hi>Command and teach</hi> (ſaith he to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.11.) There is a power <hi>directive</hi> given him: <hi>Them that ſin rebuke before all, that the reſt alſo may feare,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.10. there is his power <hi>coactive.</hi> And to <hi>Titus</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Theſe things ſpeak and exhort, and rebuke with all authority, Tit.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Teach,</hi> there is his authority to informe and direct; but is this all? No, <hi>Rebuke</hi> too, there is power to cenſure the diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient. But how <hi>rebuke?</hi> not with <hi>weak words</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for that belongs to the <hi>inferiour</hi> Clergy; but with <hi>all authority;</hi> that is, with <hi>cenſures</hi> &amp; deeds, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the <hi>ſtopping</hi> of mouths, if need be, as we may
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:4314:24"/> ſee, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.11. Nor doth S. <hi>Paul</hi> give theſe his <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> any greater allowance, than he knew his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter would warrant; for he was not ignorant of what with his owne mouth he had uttered, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17, 18. <hi>Goe tell the Church, and if he neglect to heare the Church, let him be unto thee as a heathen man, and a publican. Verily, verily I ſay unto you, whatſoever ye ſhall binde on earth, ſhall be bound in heaven, &amp;c.</hi> In which words, 1. Our <hi>Lord ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth</hi> a <hi>Tribunall</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> to which offenders againſt the Church muſt be <hi>cited,</hi> and by it <hi>cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Goe tell the Church.</hi> 2. He <hi>ratifies</hi> and ſetleth it: <hi>whatſoever ye binde on earth, &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i.</hi> whomſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you caſt out for neglect, or contempt of that authority which I have given you, ſhall be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an outcaſt in the kingdome of heaven: and by conſequent, whatſoever other puniſhment you juſtly inflict, ſhall be authorized in the higheſt <hi>Court,</hi> by the higheſt judge. <hi>What will you</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.21.) <hi>ſhall I come unto you with a rod, or in love and in the ſpirit of meekneſſe?</hi> that is, will you be perſwaded by faire words, or ſhall I exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe my <hi>Iudiciall</hi> authority over you, ſhall I puniſh you? For, as the <hi>rod</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſignifies his <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> to <hi>rule</hi> his ſervants, and <hi>ſubdue</hi> his enemies, and therefore is called the <hi>rod</hi> of his <hi>ſtrength,</hi> Pſal. 110.2. So doth the <hi>rod</hi> of S. <hi>Paul</hi> here ſignifie his <hi>puniſhing power,</hi> as S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> expound the place. And (which is a thing that ſhould work with us) this is alſo the <hi>doctrine</hi> of our <hi>owne</hi> Church, to the truth of which wee (my brethren) of the Clergy have ſubſcribed.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:4314:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Whoſoever</hi> (ſaith the Article) <hi>by his private judgement, willingly and purpoſely doth openly breake the traditions and ceremonies of the Church, which be not repugnant to the word of God, and be approved by common authority, ought to be rebuked openly, (that others may feare to doe the like) as he that offendeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the common order of the Church, and hurteth the authority of the magiſtrate, and woundeth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of weak brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſhall we not thinke that the <hi>Church</hi> hath need of this <hi>latter</hi> power, as well as the <hi>common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth?</hi> Are people ſo well affected to the orders of the Church, that they will obey them if they be but <hi>barely</hi> propounded, or at moſt, by a few perſwaſions <hi>commended</hi> to their obedience? Is the Church ſo <hi>ſetled</hi> by divine goodneſſe, that no <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly</hi> windes within her bowels can make her <hi>quake?</hi> Or is the King of the Church ſo careleſſe of his flock which he hath purchaſed with his owne blood, that he hath given it <hi>weaker</hi> ſupports than Kingdomes and civill States enjoy? and hath ſet over it <hi>ſhepheards</hi> indeed, but yet <hi>lame</hi> ones, that <hi>cannot</hi> or <hi>muſt</hi> not ſtrike if there be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion?</p>
            <p>Certainly, this earthly <hi>Paradiſe</hi> would ſoon be entred and waſted, were not thoſe <hi>Angels</hi> that are ſet to keepe the <hi>doore,</hi> armed with a <hi>flaming</hi> ſword of <hi>vindicative</hi> power, to <hi>keep</hi> out, or <hi>drive</hi> out all thoſe that either <hi>profeſſedly,</hi> or <hi>ſecretly</hi> have evill will to <hi>Sion.</hi> And therefore we cannot think with reaſon that Church-governours have the place of commanding, but no power of compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:4314:25"/> and urging obedience to their commands.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Lords of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, &amp;c. no argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Churches primitive power.</note>But they that would have a <hi>parity</hi> in the Church, and would make Church governours to be but empty <hi>Cyphers,</hi> alledge the ſpeech of our <hi>Saviour</hi> to his diſciples (<hi>contending</hi> among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for <hi>ſuperiority</hi>) Mat. 20.25, 26, 17. <hi>The Lords of the Gentiles exerciſe dominion over them, and they that are great, exerciſe authority over them: but it ſhall not be ſo among you. But whoſoever will be great among you, let him be your miniſter, and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever would be chiefe among you, let him be your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, &amp;c.</hi> And ſay, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> here <hi>compares</hi> the world and his Church, and <hi>forbids</hi> the uſe of <hi>that</hi> power to the <hi>Paſtors</hi> of the one, which belongs to the <hi>Princes</hi> of the other, and that is principally a <hi>punitive</hi> and coactive power.</p>
            <p>For the removall therefore of this <hi>Gorgons</hi> head, which doth ſo amaze the <hi>vulgar,</hi> and make them think that Biſhops ſhould uſe no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the <hi>ſafeguard</hi> of their determinations, two things are to be noted.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The <hi>perſons</hi> which are here compared and diſtinguiſhed.</item>
               <item>2. The <hi>drift</hi> and purpoſe of our <hi>Saviour</hi> in this compariſon.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. For the <hi>perſons,</hi> we are to know, that they are not <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> the <hi>Clergy</hi> and the <hi>Laity,</hi> but <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Pagan</hi> governours, as appeares by the <hi>notation</hi> of the word; for where doth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifie <hi>lay men,</hi> men diſtinguiſhed by their callings in the Church, not nations divided from the Church? It is alwayes <hi>oppoſed</hi> to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:4314:25"/> Church, and men living therein, whether miniſters or people, and is as much in ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: for the <hi>Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint</hi> doe alwayes tranſlate <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as we may ſee <hi>Eſay</hi> 11.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now <hi>Goijm</hi> ſignifies all nations that were not <hi>Iews,</hi> all ſuch, as they eſteemed to be <hi>out</hi> of the <hi>Church:</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Buxtorf. le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xic de vocab.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Iudaei ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellant Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anos <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, quaſi Gentem abommabilem, affectu proiſus malitioſo.</note> 
               <hi>Iews</hi> doe at this day call the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> becauſe they account them the <hi>greateſt</hi> ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens from the <hi>common-wealth</hi> of <hi>Iſrael, Goijm, unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving</hi> people.</p>
            <p>Beſides, if we looke into the new Teſtament, we ſhall ſee that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are never uſed, but where <hi>Gentiles</hi> are mentioned, and muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.15.10.5. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.32. <hi>Act</hi> 4.27.9 15.13 46. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.24.3.9 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Our Saviour therefore muſt have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenhere very improperly, and far otherwiſe than the language did lead him, had he by <hi>Gentiles</hi> in this place meant <hi>lay</hi> men.</p>
            <p>The compariſon therefore which is here made, being between <hi>Infidels,</hi> and the <hi>Church indefinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> (as it includes all her members and magiſtrates civill and Eccleſiaſticall) it followeth, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint here given doth not reſpect the <hi>Prelates</hi> of the Church <hi>determinately,</hi> but <hi>equally all</hi> that beare rule in Chriſtian Common-wealths; and ſo can be no argument for the <hi>clipping</hi> of the Churches wings, more than for the <hi>limiting</hi> of civill autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for the <hi>ſcope</hi> of our Saviour, it was not:</p>
            <p n="1">1. To <hi>forbid magiſtracy</hi> among Chriſtians (as the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> would have it) for then, there would be a plain <hi>contradiction</hi> between <hi>him</hi> and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:4314:26"/> his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who taught that <hi>the higher powers are ordained by God, and that they were to be obeyed by all that were under them</hi> 
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14, 17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>: and this would have brought the whole world into <hi>confuſion</hi> long ſince, there being no poſſibility of its conſiſtence without government.</p>
            <p>Nor ſecondly, was it his purpoſe to forbid a <hi>ſuperiority</hi> of ſome over others in the Church; for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. He forbids that only which himſelfe did <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe,</hi> propounding his owne <hi>practiſe</hi> as an <hi>example</hi> of that <hi>doctrine</hi> which he taught them: <hi>It ſhall not be ſo among you, for I am among you, as he that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth.</hi> But did he ever <hi>renounce</hi> authority over his diſciples while he lived among them? did not he rather behave himſelf as a <hi>commander</hi> and maſter, <hi>enjoyning</hi> them from time to time what he would have them doe? and did not he willingly accept that title of <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>maſter,</hi> which his diſciples gave him? John 13.13. <hi>Yee call me maſter and Lord, and ye ſay well; for ſo I am.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He prohibites not what he <hi>ſuppoſed;</hi> but hee ſuppoſeth that there was to be a <hi>ſub</hi> and <hi>ſupra,</hi> a ſubordination and ſuperiority among them, as the words <hi>maximus</hi> and <hi>minimus, greateſt</hi> and <hi>leaſt</hi> here uſed doe import.</p>
            <p>Neither was it, in the third place, to hinder the <hi>annexion</hi> of <hi>civill</hi> authority to the Church, and to reſtraine <hi>Church-men</hi> from being <hi>Iuſtices of peace,</hi> or <hi>privy Counſellours, &amp;c.</hi> For Chriſt doth uſe this ſpeech to his diſciples to diſſwade them from ſtriving about ſuperiority: but if this had been his meaning, that the diſciples ſhould not
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:4314:26"/> be ambitious of <hi>temporall</hi> power, it would not have <hi>reached home,</hi> nor been a ſufficient argument for that purpoſe; for they might have reaſonably <hi>replyed:</hi> Sir, we ſtrive not to be <hi>Kings</hi> or Princes, or Counſellers of State, let us have authority in the <hi>Church,</hi> and we ask no more.</p>
            <p>What then was our Saviours intent in this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition?<note place="margin">The true meaning of that Text.</note> It was to prevent the <hi>vicious cuſtoms of heathen Kings and Lords</hi> in Chriſtian Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whether <hi>ſpirituall</hi> or <hi>temporall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their vices or <hi>faults</hi> in government were eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>two.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Their ruling by their <hi>owne wills</hi> in ſtead of laws.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their ruling for their <hi>owne ends,</hi> without reſpect to the peoples good, as if the lives, and goods, and children, and ſervants of their ſubjects had been made only to ſerve their turnes, and maintaine their pomp.</p>
            <p>This was their chiefe fault, and thus did they governe, as appeares by the ſpeech of <hi>Samuel</hi> 
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Sam. <hi>8.11</hi> This will be the cuſtome of the King that ſhall raigne over you; He will take your ſons and appoint them for himſelf, for his chariots, for his horſemen, &amp;c. and your daughters for his confectionaries, cookes and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, &amp;c.</note>, who ſought to deterre the people from deſiring a <hi>King,</hi> by deſcribing <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>cuſtome</hi> and faſhion of their <hi>King</hi> treading in the ſteps of his neighbour princes, who were all <hi>Ethnicks.</hi> And ſo much doth the <hi>Originall</hi> word, by which their manner of governing is here deſcribed, import, which <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they <hi>play the Lords,</hi> they domineere over their people, as if they had all that ſoveraignty over them that can be imagined. This <hi>poteſtatem</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this vicious and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable manner of ruling, our Lord would have
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:4314:27"/> his diſciples and all Chriſtians to take heed of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing them in the meane time, <hi>poteſtatem</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>fatherly</hi> kinde of power over their inferiours, to governe as parents doe their children, with an eye on their good, and conſequently, to correct and puniſh them when they prove bad children and unruly.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Shepherds</hi> of the Church may governe their <hi>flocks,</hi> but not with <hi>force and cruelty,</hi> as they did in <hi>Ezekiels</hi> time, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.4. they may take the <hi>overſight</hi> of Gods heritage, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2. but not as abſolute Lords, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>over-ruling</hi> them (ſaith the tranſlation in the margine) for their owne, either covetous, or ambitious ends.</p>
            <p>Lay theſe two things then together. 1. <hi>Chriſt compareth</hi> the <hi>Gentiles</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in their <hi>kinde</hi> of governing: and 2. His <hi>intent</hi> is to <hi>barre</hi> all Chriſtian <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Prelates</hi> from exerciſing a <hi>tyrannicall</hi> rule over their inferiours, and to <hi>win</hi> them to that <note n="(b)" place="margin">Moderatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae poteſtatis, &amp; illius rectum uſum ad divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae voluntatis praeſcriptum ea verba docent. <hi>Pilſon. de eccl. Guber. c.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 91.</note> 
               <hi>moderation</hi> in their government, that becomes his people; and it will appeare, that this place makes nothing at all againſt the <hi>Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> of the Church or that <hi>vindicative</hi> power w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the mildeſt and moſt indulgent parents that are, doe uſe upon their children for their good; and Church, as well as civill magiſtrates, may exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe upon diſobedient perſons for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>publique</hi> peace and unity.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Puniſhments impoſed on non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions.</note>Let no man therefore ſay, when <hi>Biſhops</hi> correct <hi>oppoſers</hi> of their orders and authority, that the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders thus puniſht are <hi>martyrs,</hi> and the poore <hi>perſecuted</hi> ſheep of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and the governours that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:4314:27"/> puniſh them are <hi>wolves</hi> and <hi>perſecutors,</hi> as ſome il-affected ones ſtick not to mutter.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> writing to <hi>Rogatian</hi> a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> who had been abuſed by a ſawcy <hi>deacon,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cypr ep. ad Bogat.</hi> 65. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ptamus &amp; cup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſingulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum clementi pattentia vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, quam ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tali licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia vind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> 1. <hi>commends</hi> him becauſe he had ſought to reforme him by Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>clemency,</hi> rather than Epiſcopall <hi>authority:</hi> then he <hi>adviſeth</hi> him, if the <hi>Deacon</hi> continued in his miſdemeanour, to curb and puniſh him by <hi>depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or <hi>excommunication,</hi> 
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copatus vigore, &amp; cathedrae au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate.</note> according to his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and place. For if S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to <hi>Timothy, Let no man deſpiſe thy youth;</hi> how much more might thy fellow Biſhops (ſaith S. <hi>Cyprian</hi>) ſay to thee, <hi>Let no man deſpiſe thy age:</hi> Was this uncivill <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi> a <hi>Martyr,</hi> or S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> a <hi>perſecutor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Vigilantius</hi> a <hi>Prieſt</hi> had much <hi>misbeha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> himſelfe in point of doctrine and manners, <note n="(c)" place="margin">Hier. ep. ad Vigil.</note> S. <hi>Hierom</hi> wondereth that the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> in whoſe dioceſſe he lived, did not <hi>Virga Apoſtolica &amp; fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea confringere vas inutile, break that unprofitable peece with the iron rod of his Apoſtolique authority, Et tradere in interitum carnis, ut ſpiritus ſalvus fiat, and deliver him to the deſtruction of the fleſh, that the ſpirit might be ſaved,</hi> .i. <hi>excommunicate</hi> him. <note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.5.</note> And a little after, turning his ſpeech to <hi>Vigilanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> he cryes out (ſomewhat too paſſionately like himſelfe) <hi>O praecidendam linguam medicis, O tongue worthy to be cut out by</hi> ſpirituall <hi>phyſitians; ut qui lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui neſcit, diſcat aliquando reticere; that he who knows not how to ſpeake aright, might learne at laſt to hold his peace.</hi> Was the <hi>delinquent</hi> here a <hi>martyr,</hi> and his <hi>purſuer</hi> S. <hi>Hierom</hi> a <hi>perſecutor?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goulartius</hi> and the reſt of the Geneva <hi>Conſiſtory
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:4314:28"/> deprived Rotarius</hi> one of their miniſters, and thruſt him out of their City, and (which is more) they <hi>hunted</hi> him by their <hi>letters</hi> out of a <hi>town</hi> not far from thence, which had entertained him for their <hi>Paſtor.</hi> And why did the <hi>Conſiſtory</hi> ſo ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proſecute this man? for giving the <hi>Cup</hi> in his <hi>owne</hi> Church with his <hi>owne</hi> hands, and not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a <hi>lay</hi> man to <hi>deliver</hi> it. This fact of his was the breach of a Church-<hi>cuſtome</hi> only, but of <hi>no ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> and yet thus ſharply did they puniſh it. Were <hi>Goulartius</hi> and the <hi>Presbitery</hi> perſecutors, and that good man a <hi>martyr?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or were the <note n="(c)" place="margin">Vid. Morin. de conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eccl.</note> 
               <hi>decrees</hi> made by ſundry anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>councills</hi> for the <hi>ſuſpenſion, depoſition,</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication</hi> of <hi>unruly</hi> miniſters, <hi>perſecutions?</hi> I thinke our ſcrupulous mindes will not ſay ſo, for <hi>Non omnis qui parcit amicus eſt, nec omnis qui verberat inimicus; Every one that ſpares is not a friend, nor every one that puniſheth an enemy.</hi> But if any can ſo caſt off modeſty, as to brand theſe wholſome judiciary Acts and Canons with the diſgracefull name of perſecutions, our Reverend Fathers may the more contentedly put up the like aſperſions, conſidering <hi>that this affliction that befalls them, hath been accompliſhed in their elder bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> O, but the miniſters uſually <hi>ſuſpended,</hi> are good men, and therefore, we may well ſay, they are perſecuted.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 1. <hi>Some</hi> of them, no doubt, <hi>are</hi> ſo; and if they be,<note place="margin">Inconformity is accidental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a great ſin.</note> they ſhall reap the <hi>profit</hi> of it another day; it is poſſible ſometimes for good men to tread
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:4314:28"/> awry, being caryed away with the ſtreame of <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pularity,</hi> and mis-led by the hope of <hi>gaine</hi> or <hi>glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Whether</hi> they be all good or no, I leave it to be <hi>decided</hi> by the <hi>ſearcher</hi> of all hearts; only thus much in the generall I am ſure of, that <hi>Multi ſunt in ſanctorum catalogo, qui non ſunt in conſortio, many are now accounted Saints, which will not goe for Saints at that day when all ſecrets ſhall be manifeſted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It is not their goodneſſe that is puniſhed, but their badneſſe; S. <hi>Peter</hi> intimates, that a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> may be detected and puniſhed for an <hi>evill</hi> doer, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.15, 16. If good <hi>men</hi> will have their hands in bad <hi>cauſes,</hi> their goodneſſe muſt not make them <hi>law-proofe,</hi> and beare them off from the ſtroke of juſtice. <hi>Cauſa, non poena,</hi> (I may adde <hi>nec perſona) facit martyrem, it is the cauſe, not the puniſhment</hi> (no nor the perſon neither) <hi>that makes the martyr. Inexpiable and great is the ſinne of ſchiſme and diſcord in the Church</hi> (ſaith S. <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cypr. de unit. Eccl.</hi> Inexprabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis &amp; gravis cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa diſcordiae, nec paſſione purgatur.</note> 
               <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an) and cannot be purged even with martyrdome.</hi> And a <note n="(b)" place="margin">Ardeant licet ſlammis &amp; ignibus, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diti vel objecti beſtus animas ſuas ponant; non<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t illa fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ona, ſed poena perfidiae; nec religioſae virtutis exitus glorioſus, ſed d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tus. Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alis poteſt, cotona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i non poteſt.</note> little after, ſpeaking of ſuch as lived contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in the Church, he ſaith, <hi>Ardeant licet ſlam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, &amp;c. Though they breath out their ſoules at a ſtake, or under the teeth of wilde beaſts, their goodnes is not crowned, but their perſidiouſneſſe puniſht. Occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di talis poteſt, coronari non poteſt. Such a man may bee killed, but crowned he cannot be. Martyrs are they</hi> (ſaith S. <note n="(c)" place="margin">Aug. ep. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtin) which ſuffer, not for diſorder, and the ungodly breach of Chriſtian unity, but for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe ſake: for Hagar was perſecuted by Sarah, and yet ſhe that did impoſe was holy, and ſhe was the unrighteous perſon that did beare the burden: If things
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:4314:29"/> be rightly ſcanned</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Hagar did perſecute Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah more by proud reſiſtance, than Sarah her by infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting deſerved vengeance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> Yea, but the fault of <hi>inconformity</hi> (if it bee a fault) is but a <hi>ſmall</hi> one, &amp; yet <hi>more grievouſly</hi> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, than <hi>ſwearing, drunkenneſſe, uncleanneſſe, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury,</hi> and many other ſinnes which farre exceed this; want of <hi>proportion</hi> therefore between the <hi>fault</hi> and the <hi>penalty,</hi> maketh thoſe puniſhments to be no better than perſecutions.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Sinnes or faults may bee conſidered in their <hi>nature,</hi> or in their <hi>manner</hi> of committing, and thoſe ill <hi>conſequents</hi> that ſpring from them: and a ſinne that is little and leaſt in the firſt, may bee great and greateſt in thoſe laſt reſpects; and ſo is this ſinne of which we are ſpeaking. If we looke upon it in its owne <hi>nature,</hi> it is nothing ſo foule a ſinne as is murder, adultery, perjury, &amp;c. for this is a ſinne by <hi>accident,</hi> becauſe againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of authority; thoſe other <hi>eſſentially</hi> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally, becauſe damned by the light of nature. But if we behold it in the <hi>manner</hi> of committing, it is a greater; this being <hi>ſeldome</hi> committed, <hi>never</hi> puniſht, without <hi>wilfulneſſe</hi> and obſtinacy, they many times breaking out through meere <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and infirmity. And ſo it is in reſpect of its <hi>dangerouſneſſe</hi> in the <hi>iſſue.</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is a <hi>bold faced</hi> ſinne, that <hi>Ionah</hi>-like ſtands alwayes upon its <hi>juſtification,</hi> and pleads <hi>not guilty,</hi> and caſts a blemiſh upon that <hi>authority</hi> that dares cenſure it. Theſe other are ſinnes (as more foule, ſo) more modeſt, leſſe confident; like the <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:4314:29"/> in <hi>Titus</hi> 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſelf-convicted</hi> and <hi>ſelf-condemned,</hi> and meet with fewer Patrons.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe ſinnes fight againſt Church-<hi>govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> by <hi>conſequent</hi> only, this <hi>directly;</hi> and if it be not in time reſtrained, brings confuſion and <hi>Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> into the Church. Like <hi>Peters</hi> diſſimulation, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. it ſowreth a multitude in a moment: like a <hi>gangren,</hi> if it <hi>ſeize,</hi> and be permitted to <hi>ſettle</hi> but on one limb, it ſpeedily <hi>runnes</hi> over, and ruines all the body; men too ſinfully affecting (ſince the fall) to be <hi>Domini ſuorum actuum, Lords over their owne actions in all things,</hi> and to ſhake off the yoke of government.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe ſinnes goe many times <hi>alone,</hi> this <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver;</hi> but like a <hi>fury</hi> brings a <hi>troope</hi> of miſchiefes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it. It makes <hi>diviſions</hi> and breaches in other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe peaceable <hi>congregations;</hi> begets <hi>diſcords, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts</hi> in people of their learned, able, and wel-deſerving <hi>Paſtors.</hi> It breeds <hi>emulations</hi> alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>brethren</hi> of the ſame <hi>Tribe, miniſters</hi> of the ſame <hi>Chriſt;</hi> even to the ſharpning of <hi>tongues</hi> and <hi>pens</hi> againſt each other, till like the <hi>Cadmean</hi> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, <hi>mutuis vulneribus confoſsi cadunt</hi> (as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſpeakes) they fall to the ground by their own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brotherly wounds.</p>
            <p>This makes ſome ſtand <hi>neuters</hi> and <hi>look on,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers turne <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>deride;</hi> this makes our <hi>friends lament</hi> us, and our <hi>adverſaries triumph</hi> over us, while they hope to ſee our <hi>Church</hi> diſſolved, without either plots or pens of theirs, by our <hi>own unnaturall</hi> broyles and contentions. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is many wayes a greater ſinne than they,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:4314:30"/> and worthy of condigne puniſhment.</p>
            <p>To conclude this point, take an <hi>eſtimate</hi> of this ſinne from God himſelfe: Did not he <hi>reveale</hi> his wrath from <hi>heaven</hi> even againſt <hi>Miriam,</hi> and ſmite her with leproſie, &amp; excommunication for a time, for oppoſing but with one weak word, or two, the authority of her brother <hi>Moſes, Num.</hi> 12? was not <hi>Korah</hi> and his ſeditious company conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with fire from heaven, and made <hi>Horrenda victima nil miſerantis orci,</hi> a lamentable <hi>ſacrifice</hi> to the <hi>gaping earth</hi> in a moment? and why, but for <hi>denying</hi> obedience to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a <hi>rent</hi> in the congregation? <hi>Quis dubitat ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leratius eſſe commiſſum, quod gravius eſt punitum? Who doubts</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Hierome) that the ſinne which was ſo fearefully puniſhed, was as highly deteſted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Leave off therefore theſe ſcandalous crimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which have in them neither <hi>truth</hi> nor <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cypr. de unit.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that ſeq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>? g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atul <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> lum e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nata <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar.</note> and ſeek not to make <hi>juſtice</hi> odious with ſuch <hi>nick-names</hi> of tyranny and <hi>perſecution.</hi> As great a woe is due to ſuch as call <hi>good evill,</hi> as to them that call <hi>evill good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid facit in pectore, &amp;c. What doth the wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of wolves, and the madneſſe of dogs</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian) in Chriſtian breaſts? the poyſon of ſerpents, and the cruelty of beaſts, why ſhould they lodge there?</hi> Would ye be counted <hi>Saints?</hi> what have <hi>Saints</hi> to doe with ſuch angry and <hi>uncharitable</hi> paſſions? <hi>tant aene animis coeleſtibus irae?</hi> would ye be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med men of the <hi>ſpirit?</hi> what fellowſhip hath the <hi>meek</hi> Spirit of <hi>God</hi> with the <hi>malicious</hi> ſpirit of the <hi>devill? Spiritus Dei nec mendax, nec mordax,</hi> the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:4314:30"/> Spirit of God, neither <hi>belies</hi> nor <hi>bites,</hi> as they doe who call deſerved puniſhments perſecutions:<note place="margin">Hier. ep. ad Vigil.</note> for <hi>Noneſt crudelitas pro Deo pietas, Zeale for God and the Churches peace, is no cruelty,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Hierome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I come to my laſt Conſectary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ceremonies and orders impoſed by Church gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours on inferiour miniſters and people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5. <hi>Conſectary</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>muſt be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:</hi> For <hi>power</hi> in them to <hi>enjoyne,</hi> by the law of <hi>Relatives</hi> inferres in us a <hi>neceſsity</hi> to <hi>obey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are 3. ſorts of things and actions (ſaith <note n="(a)" place="margin">Aug. l. <hi>3.</hi> de lib. Arb. c. <hi>18, 19</hi>
               </note> S. <hi>Auſtin.</hi>)</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some <hi>intrinſecally</hi> and <hi>eſſentially good,</hi> which cannot bee <hi>evill at any time;</hi> ſuch are <hi>vertues</hi> and vertuous acts; which, though they may be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with <hi>evill</hi> ends, and ſo <hi>non redundare in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonam, not redound to the good of the doer,</hi> can <hi>never</hi> be <hi>bad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Some <hi>internally</hi> and <hi>eſſentially evill;</hi> which are not therefore <hi>evill,</hi> becauſe <hi>prohibited,</hi> as the eating of the <hi>forbidden</hi> tree, and <hi>Sauls</hi> ſparing of the <hi>Amalekites</hi> were; but <hi>prohibited</hi> becauſe <hi>evill,</hi> as <hi>perjury, murder, adultery,</hi> and other <hi>ſins</hi> againſt the light of <hi>nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Other things there are of a <hi>middle</hi> nature, neither <hi>good</hi> nor <hi>evill</hi> in <hi>themſelves,</hi> but eaſily <hi>changeable</hi> into good or evill by <hi>concomitant cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances.</hi> Of this ſort are <hi>Rites</hi> and ceremonies, ordained by the Church to bee uſed <hi>in</hi> or <hi>about</hi> Gods ſervice. In <hi>themſelves,</hi> they are like <hi>faſtings, watchings,</hi> and ſuch other <hi>bodily caſtigations,</hi> which (conſidered in the naked act) are affirmed to bee <hi>unprofitable,</hi> and <hi>diſtinguiſhed</hi> from true <hi>godlineſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:4314:31"/> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. neither <hi>pleaſing</hi> nor <hi>diſpleaſing</hi> to God: yet, <hi>ſub mandato,</hi> as they are by lawfull au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority <hi>enjoyned,</hi> they become <hi>neceſſary,</hi> and <hi>attin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt conſcientiam,</hi> lay an <hi>obligation</hi> of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on the <hi>conſcience.</hi> For we reade, that <hi>Idolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thytes, things ſtrangled,</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi> though they were in themſelves <hi>indifferent</hi> meates, and might be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten or not eaten without <hi>offence</hi> of conſcience; yet when they had the <hi>ſtamp</hi> of a negative <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> upon them, and were for certaine reaſons <hi>prohibited</hi> by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> they were called <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary things, Acts</hi> 15.28. <hi>It ſeemes good, &amp;c. to lay upon you no greater burden than theſe neceſſary things; Neceſſary,</hi> for the avoiding of <hi>ſcandall; neceſſary</hi> through the <hi>command</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> reſtraining their uſe for the <hi>time,</hi> though in themſelves indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorting to obedience of authority, ſaith, <hi>Ye muſt be ſubject, not becauſe of wrath only, but for conſcience ſake, Rom.</hi> 13.5. gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us to underſtand, that even theſe <hi>ſmaller</hi> things, when they are once <hi>commanded,</hi> doe <hi>reach</hi> the <hi>conſcience,</hi> and cannot be <hi>omitted</hi> without ſome <hi>violation</hi> of it. Neceſſity of obedience ariſeth ſometimes <hi>ex natura rei,</hi> from the <hi>nature</hi> of the thing commanded, as in all <hi>morall</hi> precepts; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>ex vi mandati,</hi> from the <hi>power</hi> by which they are <hi>enjoyned,</hi> as in all <hi>poſitive</hi> laws and commands, whether <hi>civill</hi> or <hi>ceremoniall.</hi> And ſo it doth here, to wit, from a double <hi>power.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>Governour</hi> commanding theſe things to be done.</item>
               <item>2. The <hi>power</hi> of <hi>God</hi> authorizing him to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:4314:31"/> and obliging inferiours to obey.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Obedience then to theſe ſmaller things of the law, theſe appendices of Gods ſervice, (<hi>Surpleſſe, Hood, ſtanding</hi> up at the Creed, <hi>kneeling</hi> at the Communion, the <hi>Croſſe</hi> in baptiſme, and <hi>bowing</hi> at the name of <hi>Ieſus</hi>) is no arbitrary and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent thing. <hi>But it is the part of ever private man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 30.</note> 
               <hi>both miniſter and other, reverently to retaine the true uſe of theſe things preſcribed by publique authority; conſidering, that things of themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> different, doe in ſome ſort alter their natures, when they are either commanded or forbidden by a lawfull magiſtrate; and may not be omitted at every mans pleaſure, contrary to the law, when they be commanded; nor uſed when they are prohibited.</hi> They are the laſt words of our 30. <hi>Canon,</hi> and a confirmation of my point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let every ſoule</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul) be ſubject to the higher powers;</hi> the words are not <hi>permiſsive,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom</hi> 13.</note> let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that <hi>will,</hi> ſubject himſelfe to authority, but <hi>imperative,</hi> let every one as he <hi>ought, ſubmit</hi> himſelfe. And, <hi>let every ſoule;</hi> here is no liberty for <hi>libertiniſme</hi> in any: none muſt think himſelfe too <hi>great,</hi> or too <hi>good</hi> to yeeld obedience to his <hi>ſuperiours,</hi> all without exception, or exemption, muſt doe their commands. And therefore I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how thoſe that ſeem to make a conſcience of <hi>other</hi> ſinnes, can make no conſcience of <hi>this,</hi> but rather make it a point of conſcience to lye under this <hi>guilt,</hi> and be rebellious againſt their lawfull <hi>Paſtors</hi> in theſe things. <hi>Obey them</hi> (ſaith the ſame <hi>Apoſtle, Heb</hi> 13.17.) <hi>that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves:</hi> the <hi>perſons</hi> here pointed
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:4314:32"/> at, are <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Prelates</hi> of the Church, as the following words doe ſhew, (for to them alone doth the care of mens ſoules <hi>directly</hi> and properly belong) and the <hi>duty</hi> which all inferiours owe to them, is obedience, which therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth not barely commend, but peremptorily charge upon them. But a place that may be inſtead of all others to inforce obedience to the <hi>laws</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and a full and ample obedience alſo to all good laws is, that <hi>Text</hi> in S. <hi>Matthew,</hi> where our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaith: <hi>The Scribes and Phariſees ſit in Moſes ſeate:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23 2.</note> 
               <hi>all therefore whatſoever they bid you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that obſerve and doe, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe words there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt a little be examined, and <hi>preſſed</hi> upon our refractory brethren. Firſt then, <hi>who</hi> are the <hi>perſons</hi> to whom ſubjection is here injoyned? the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phriſees;</hi> but <hi>who</hi> were they?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What is meant by Scribes and Phariſees.</note>
               <hi>Scribe</hi> in Scripture is a name of <hi>office</hi> or <hi>calling,</hi> and ſignifies 3. ſorts of men. 1. A <hi>Scrivener,</hi> one that liveth by writing, ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. 1. <hi>My tongue is the tongue of a ready writer.</hi> 2. A <hi>Secretary</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> in this ſenſe <hi>Shebna</hi> is called a <hi>Scribe, Eſay</hi> 36.3. 3. An <hi>officer</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> an <hi>expounder</hi> and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> in this ſenſe <hi>Ezra</hi> the <hi>Prieſt</hi> is ſaid to be a <hi>ready Scribe in the Law of Moſes, Ezra</hi> 7.6. .i. <hi>a skilfull interpreter:</hi> ſo it is alſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.52. <hi>Every Scribe which is inſtructed to the kingdome of heaven, &amp;c.</hi> And in this laſt ſenſe it is to be taken here.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phariſee,</hi> is a name of <hi>Sect</hi> or <hi>Order,</hi> and the <hi>Phariſees</hi> were a <hi>fraternity</hi> among the <hi>Iews,</hi> that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by peculiar rules, and in a <hi>ſtricter</hi> manner
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:4314:32"/> than did others. As we may ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 26.5. where S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, <hi>After the ſtraiteſt ſect of our religion, I lived a Phariſee.</hi> Of theſe <hi>Phariſees</hi> ſome were <hi>Clergy</hi>-men, <hi>Scribes,</hi> and <hi>expounders</hi> of the law, as it appeares, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.10, 11. where <hi>Nicodemus</hi> is called a <hi>Phariſee,</hi> and a <hi>maſter</hi> or <hi>teacher</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Acts</hi> 5.34. where <hi>Gamaliel</hi> is called a <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee,</hi> and a <hi>Doctor</hi> of the law, .i. an <hi>expounder</hi> of the <hi>Scripture.</hi> So that theſe two differed, as the <hi>Secular</hi> and <hi>Regular</hi> Prieſts, they lived after a di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver, manner yet both of them were <hi>Teachers,</hi> and in <hi>ſpirituall</hi> things Rulers and <hi>Maſters</hi> of the people.</p>
            <p>We ſee who the <hi>perſons</hi> are to be obeyed. But <hi>why</hi> muſt they be obeyed? becauſe, ſaith <hi>Chriſt, They ſit in Moſes ſeat.</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">1</hi> We reade of a <hi>twofold ſeate, peculiar</hi> to perſons of quality and <hi>eminency</hi> of place.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A <hi>ſeate</hi> of <hi>civill</hi> government,<note place="margin">What is meant by Moſes chayre.</note> belonging to <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Iudges,</hi> as may be ſeen <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.5. <hi>There are ſet Thrones of judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A <hi>ſeate</hi> of <hi>doctrine</hi> and ſpirituall <hi>Iuriſdiction, proper</hi> to the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and heads of the Church; for ſuch were wont to <hi>ſit</hi> when they <hi>taught</hi> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and gave <hi>judgement,</hi> as our <hi>Saviour</hi> intimates, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.55. <hi>I ſate daily among you, teaching in the Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> of theſe ſeats was uſually called the <hi>Throne of David,</hi> becauſe he was the <hi>firſt</hi> eſtabliſht <hi>King,</hi> to whom God had appointed a <hi>ſucceſsion</hi> of <hi>children</hi> to be <hi>Kings</hi> after him: but this latter ſeat, the <hi>Chaire</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> becauſe he was the <hi>firſt</hi> that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:4314:33"/> 
               <hi>received</hi> the law from God, and <hi>publiſhed</hi> it to the <hi>people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To <hi>ſit</hi> in theſe ſeats is, to <hi>ſucceed</hi> theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in <hi>authority;</hi> to ſit in <hi>Davids Throne,</hi> is to <hi>ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed</hi> him in his <hi>kingdome,</hi> and therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> is ſaid to ſit in the throne of <hi>David</hi> his father, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee did ſucceed him in his royall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and to <hi>ſit</hi> in the <hi>chaire</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> is to have the place and <hi>office</hi> of <hi>inſtructing</hi> and <hi>governing</hi> the people in things concerning <hi>God.</hi> So that our Saviours reaſon to urge the people to obedience is, the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> are the <hi>authorized</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and <hi>maſters</hi> of <hi>Iſrael; therefore</hi> you muſt bee ruled by them, and ſubmit unto them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Authority how far to be obeyed.</note>But <hi>thirdly, how far</hi> were the people to obey them? <hi>Whatſoever they bid you obſerve</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chriſt) that obſerve and doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words though in their <hi>forme</hi> they be <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall,</hi> yet in their <hi>ſenſe</hi> they are <hi>particular,</hi> and muſt be <hi>reſtrained</hi> by their <hi>matter.</hi> The Papiſts take them <hi>without</hi> any <hi>limitation,</hi> in a moſt <hi>ample</hi> ſenſe, to gain <hi>credit</hi> to the <hi>Popes infallibility. Others</hi> in oppoſition to them <hi>girt</hi> them up <hi>too</hi> ſhort, and ſay, that our Saviours meaning was, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould obey them in all things which they <hi>taught out of the law of Moſes.</hi> But if this were all the meaning, <hi>then</hi> they had been bound to heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to theſe Doctors ſitting in <hi>Moſes</hi> chayre, no <hi>further than</hi> to every <hi>Iuſtice ſitting</hi> on the bench, than to every <hi>Taylor ſitting</hi> on his ſhopboard, yea, and <hi>then</hi> the flock were no more bound to obey their <hi>Paſtor,</hi> than the <hi>Paſtor</hi> were to obey his <hi>flock;</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:4314:33"/> for if they admoniſh them to do any thing which is commanded in <hi>Moſes</hi> law, they were bound to obey it; not becauſe <hi>they</hi> ſaid it, but becauſe <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> did ſay it before. And if we thus conſtrue the words, then what ſhall become of this <hi>illation</hi> of our Saviour, <hi>becauſe</hi> they ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeate, <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> whatſoever they bid you doe, doe it? But what then is the meaning of theſe words? <hi>viz.</hi> That they ſhould obey them in <hi>all things belonging to the place and authority of Moſes his ſucceſſours; In omnibus ad Cathedram pertinentibus,</hi> in all things which the <hi>chaire</hi> ought to <hi>preſcribe</hi> them: as when <hi>ſervants</hi> and <hi>children</hi> are commanded to obey their <hi>maſters</hi> and <hi>parents</hi> in <hi>all things, Col.</hi> 3.20, 22. It is meant, <hi>In omnibus quae pertinent ad jus domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivae poteſtatis,</hi> ſaith <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> 22. <hi>q.</hi> 104. <hi>art.</hi> 5. <hi>ad</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Aquinas,</hi> in all things which appertaine to <hi>maſters</hi> and <hi>parents, right</hi> and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to command. Now they had authority to command:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Whatſoever</hi> was within the <hi>verge</hi> of their owne <hi>calling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Whatſoever</hi> was not <hi>repugnant</hi> to <hi>ſuperiour</hi> laws of <hi>God,</hi> or the <hi>State</hi> in which they lived, to which being but ſubordinate and <hi>delegated</hi> rulers, themſelves were ſubject as well as their people.</p>
            <p>Put all theſe now together, and the meaning of our <hi>Lord</hi> will appeare to be, <hi>That in all things belonging to their office and authority, the people were to obey the Scribes and Phariſees, who were their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Paſtors and Governours, becauſe the office of inſtructing and preſcribing was committed to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And from this <hi>charge</hi> reſulteth moſt evidently
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:4314:34"/> this faire <hi>concluſion,</hi> that it is the duty of <hi>people</hi> to <hi>ſubmit</hi> themſelves to the directions and <hi>preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of their <hi>Biſhops</hi> and ſpirituall rulers, who <hi>ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed</hi> a <hi>greater</hi> than <hi>Moſes, Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> in the <hi>overſight</hi> and government of the <hi>Church,</hi> in all ſuch things as they <hi>perſwade</hi> or <hi>preſcribe</hi> not <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> to the word of God, and the eſtabliſhed go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment wherein they live. And conſequently, it belongs to <hi>us</hi> that are inferiours (whether mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters or people) to ſubmit to thoſe orders and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> which are in the <hi>power</hi> and hands of our <hi>Prelates</hi> to <hi>preſcribe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But what if they paſſe their <hi>bounds,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand us things <hi>not</hi> lawfull.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <note place="margin">Our Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies are rightly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified.</note>I anſwer, 1. If wee bee <hi>ſure</hi> that at any time they doe ſo, we are <hi>not</hi> to obey them; for <hi>whether it be better to obey God or man, judge yee,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Acts</hi> 4.19.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In <hi>determining Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> (which are the ſubject of our diſcourſe) there is no <hi>juſt</hi> cauſe to feare that.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the <hi>conſtitution</hi> and ſpecification of things of this nature, (as hath been proved,) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaines to <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> power; and by the Kings <hi>Prerogative Royall,</hi> and <hi>ſupreme</hi> authority in cauſes <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi>) was <hi>granted</hi> and <hi>confirmed</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of our Church under the great <hi>ſeale</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as we may ſee in his laſt Majeſties <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration</hi> ſet downe <hi>before</hi> and <hi>after</hi> the booke of <hi>Canons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Becauſe the <hi>Rites</hi> in uſe among us, have all thoſe <hi>conditions</hi> in them, with which <hi>lawfull</hi> and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:4314:34"/> 
               <hi>comely</hi> ceremonies ought (as I have ſaid) to bee <hi>qualified.</hi> They are but <hi>few,</hi> ſuch as have beene <hi>leaſt abuſed,</hi> ſuch as may be altered when authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſees cauſe, and therefore not eſteemed of <hi>equall</hi> rank to the <hi>law</hi> of God: ſuch alſo as are neither <hi>dark</hi> nor <hi>dumb</hi> ceremonies, but carry their <hi>ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> in their <hi>foreheads,</hi> and therefore not <hi>eaſily li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> to any great <hi>abuſe:</hi> they are ſuch too, as are impoſed on us, without <hi>contempt</hi> or <hi>prejudice</hi> to <hi>other</hi> Churches, that <hi>uſe them not;</hi> as our <hi>Church</hi> hath been pleaſed, for the <hi>preventing</hi> of idle <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils,</hi> and the <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> of <hi>ſcrupulous</hi> mindes, with much wiſdome and tenderneſſe,<note place="margin">Whether they muſt be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a doubting of conſcience.</note> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> to <hi>declare</hi> her ſelfe in the <hi>Preface</hi> before our book of <hi>Common-prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what if we <hi>doubt</hi> (may ſome ſay) whether theſe <hi>Rites</hi> be <hi>lawfull</hi> and good, or no, muſt wee <hi>then</hi> obey?</p>
            <p n="1">1. After ſo <hi>long</hi> a time, and ſuch <hi>good</hi> meanes of information, it is not <hi>fit</hi> that any <hi>ſhould</hi> doubt, nor <hi>likely</hi> that many do doubt without much wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe. <note n="(a)" place="margin">Confer. at Hamp. Court. pag <hi>66.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>It is to be feared that ſome of them which pretend weakneſſe and doubting, are ſtrong enough, if not head-ſtrong, and ſuch as thinke themſelves able to teach the King, and all the Biſhops of the Land:</hi> they are not my words, but the ſpeech of a <hi>King,</hi> even our <hi>late Soveraigne Lord</hi> of happy memory.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Obedience <hi>muſt</hi> be yeelded to things <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded</hi> (and conſequently to theſe) notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>doubting.</hi> If a doubt be only ſpeculative, of the <hi>lawfulneſſe</hi> of ſuch things as lie in a mans own <hi>liberty</hi> to do or forbeare, then it is the <hi>ſafeſt</hi> courſe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:4314:35"/> not to doe them; for as (according to the <hi>Italian</hi> proverb) <hi>that meate which a man doth not eate, will not hurt him;</hi> ſo ſuch things as he forbeares, will not offend his conſcience: nay, in ſuch a caſe, to doe any thing doubtingly is a <hi>ſinne,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. <hi>He that doubteth is damned if he eate, becauſe he eateth not of faith: for whatſoever is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi> But if the doubt be <hi>practicall</hi> and the matter of it a thing <hi>commanded</hi> by ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors (as theſe things are, of which we are now ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king) that doubting doth neither <hi>infer</hi> nor <hi>excuſe</hi> our diſobedience. Such a man as is troubled with this <hi>kinde</hi> of doubting, if he have time and means, ſhould <hi>expell</hi> the doubt, that he may <hi>yeeld</hi> obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence where he <hi>oweth</hi> it, with cheerefulneſſe. But if he <hi>will</hi> not, or <hi>cannot</hi> expell it, the things en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned he <hi>muſt</hi> doe, the doubt <hi>remaining.</hi> For, that lawfull <hi>authority</hi> is to be <hi>obeyed,</hi> is <hi>certain,</hi> that this or that thing <hi>commanded</hi> by that authority is <hi>unlawfull,</hi> is <hi>doubtfull:</hi> Now when a <hi>doubt</hi> ſtands in <hi>competition</hi> for maſterſhip with a <hi>cleare caſe,</hi> the <hi>doubt</hi> in all reaſon muſt <hi>yeeld,</hi> and that which is cleare and <hi>certaine</hi> muſt be <hi>done;</hi> for <hi>è malis mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, of two hard choyces the beſt and ſafeſt is to bee made.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. ep.</hi> 86. <hi>ad Caſul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a.</hi> Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po tuo in hiſce noli reſiſtere, &amp; quod facit ipſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſine ullo ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulo ſectare.</note> And therefore what S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſayes to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulanus,</hi> I ſay to every one, <hi>Epiſcopo tuo in hiſce, &amp;c. withſtand not thy Dioceſan in theſe things, but what he doth, without ſcruple imitate;</hi> what he commands, obey.</p>
            <p>But what doe I talke of obeying in this <hi>licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> age; it being ſuch, that it is almoſt accounted a fault <hi>unpardonable</hi> to preach for <hi>ſubjection</hi> to the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:4314:35"/> Churches <hi>Hierarchy;</hi> and he eſteemed the <hi>pureſt</hi> man that is the <hi>greateſt ſtickler</hi> againſt it. But the ſpirit of <hi>contention</hi> will not alwayes <hi>raigne;</hi> it is pitty it ſhould: and therefore in hope to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile (at leaſt with ſome) I ſay againe, in the words of S. <hi>Hierome, Eſto ſubjectus Pontifici tuo, &amp; quaſi animae parentem ſuſcipe. Be ſubject to thy Biſhop, and reverence him as the father of thy ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Three</hi> ſorts I ſhould here <hi>perſwade</hi> to obedience; Our ſelves of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> our <hi>Church</hi>-officers, and our <hi>people.</hi> But becauſe the ſubmiſſion of the <hi>two laſt,</hi> for the moſt part <hi>ſtands</hi> and <hi>falls</hi> in <hi>ours,</hi> I ſhould hope I might the more eaſily <hi>winne them,</hi> if I could but <hi>prevaile</hi> with you (my brethren) for a compleate and cheerfull <hi>conformity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omne malum ab Aquilone,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſobedience to Church-governours begins at the Clergy.</note> if there be <hi>diſaffecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in our people, it begins too often at the <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary,</hi> for <hi>like prieſt, like people,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Prophet.</hi> The <hi>forming</hi> of childrens mindes is much in the power of the nurſe or <hi>mother,</hi> who gives them ſuck, and brings them up; and ſo are our peoples <hi>manners</hi> in theſe things ſutable to <hi>our molds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we ſhall take liberty to break unſavory <hi>jeſts</hi> upon the reverend <hi>Fathers</hi> of our Church, and their <hi>officers,</hi> and to make our ſelves and others <hi>merry</hi> with talking of the <hi>Idolatry,</hi> the <hi>adultery,</hi> the <hi>murder</hi> and the <hi>felony</hi> of the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> and other ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, as ſometimes <hi>Parker,</hi> (whether more fooliſhly or prophanely) did: if we make our <hi>Pulpits Paſquills,</hi> in them <hi>preſuming</hi> with a ſad face of ſeeming piety to <hi>traduce</hi> our Superiours, and <hi>caſt</hi> our humorous and diſcontented <hi>aſperſions</hi> in
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:4314:36"/> their <hi>faces;</hi> if wee leave out the <hi>croſſe</hi> when wee <hi>Chriſten</hi> (to pleaſure a friend, or gain a bribe) and the <hi>ſurpleſſe</hi> when we come to <hi>miniſter</hi> before the Lord, and <hi>omit</hi> ſuch <hi>other</hi> ceremonies as require our <hi>perſonable</hi> and <hi>exemplary</hi> obedience; will not our people that hang upon our <hi>hands</hi> and <hi>lips,</hi> and ſee and heare what we doe, doe likewiſe? If our <hi>breaſts</hi> ſhall daily <hi>runne</hi> downe with ſuch <hi>infecting</hi> ſtuffe, what can be expected, but that our people which lye <hi>ſucking</hi> at them, ſhould prove a <hi>crazie</hi> generation?</p>
            <p>And can it be thought, that if we (who are the <hi>watchmen</hi> of our people, and if we ſpie a <hi>lion</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming upon them, a ſinne ready to enſnare them, ſhould tell them ſo) do either <hi>diſſemble,</hi> or, which is worſe, <hi>incourage</hi> the ſin of <hi>perjury</hi> in our <hi>Church-wardens</hi> for our <hi>owne</hi> bad ends, their <hi>bills</hi> ſhould give in true <hi>evidence,</hi> and make a <hi>faithfull report</hi> of <hi>Pariſh</hi>-diſorders? It cannot bee, and therefore ſome, whom it too much concernes, may well <hi>complaine,</hi> and cry out with the <hi>Prophet, O my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they that leade thee, cauſe thee to erre, Eſay</hi> 3.12.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Not at the people except firſt perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>But me thinkes I heare <hi>Aaron</hi> charging the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with his ſin, <hi>the people, thou knoweſt, are ſet on miſchiefe, Exod.</hi> 32.22.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Ieremy</hi> complaining, that <hi>the Prophets pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie falſly, and the people love to have it ſo, Ier.</hi> 5.31. It ſhould ſeeme, the <hi>root</hi> of inconformity lyes in <hi>them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True it is, ſome miniſters <hi>deny,</hi> or <hi>curtall</hi> their <hi>conformity,</hi> and the people <hi>love</hi> to have it ſo. But <hi>what</hi> people? a people <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Juven Sat.</hi> 14.— Velocius &amp; citius nos Corrumpunt vitiorum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca magnis Cum ſubeant ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</note> 
               <hi>marred</hi> in their <hi>making,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:4314:36"/> catechized</hi> by their <hi>parents,</hi> or <hi>Paſtors</hi> with <hi>falſe</hi> principles, and <hi>taught</hi> to beleeve, that the <hi>Biſhops are limbs of Antichriſt, the Surpleſſe a rag of Popery, Conformity a mark of the Beaſt;</hi> that every good man muſt abhorre them, and pray to the <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> to <hi>ſweep</hi> them out of his <hi>ſanctuary: ſuch</hi> people love to have it ſo. And therefore it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes us miniſters, who ſhould be <hi>examples</hi> to our flocks in all good things, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. 1 To looke to our <hi>own</hi> conformity. 2 To teach <hi>our people</hi> throughly the point of obedience.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt looke to our <hi>owne</hi> conformity,<note place="margin">Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity.</note> and <hi>begin</hi> the reformation of diſorder at our <hi>ſelves;</hi> and to this, <hi>three</hi> things (me thinkes) ſhould move us:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Our <hi>ſubſcription</hi> to the <hi>Articles</hi> of our Church, and the booke of <hi>common</hi> prayer, by which wee have <hi>(ex animo)</hi> confeſſed <hi>two</hi> things: 1. that it is in the <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> (and conſequently of ours) to <hi>decree</hi> Rites and ceremonies: 2. that our <hi>ſervice</hi> book containes nothing in it <hi>repugnant</hi> to the word of God, nothing that may not be <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully</hi> uſed, and by every one ſubmitted to: and that which follows upon this, is, that our <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and orders, <hi>juſtified</hi> and <hi>impoſed</hi> in the booke of <hi>common-prayer,</hi> are <hi>agreeable</hi> to <hi>Gods</hi> word, and to be <hi>uſed</hi> by us. If we now after our <hi>often ſubſcripti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on</hi> to theſe things, ſhall <hi>refuſe</hi> or <hi>omit</hi> the <hi>uſe</hi> of them in our <hi>practiſes,</hi> will not there be a groſſe <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtency</hi> between our <hi>judgements</hi> and <hi>behaviours?</hi> doe we not <hi>condemne</hi> our ſelves in that which we <hi>allow?</hi> a courſe which God will never <hi>bleſſe,</hi> as
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:4314:37"/> we may ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.22. <hi>Bleſſed is he that condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not himſelfe in that which he alloweth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That <hi>voluntary</hi> and <hi>ſpeciall obligation</hi> which we have brought upon our ſelves in our <hi>ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> ſhould likewiſe work with us. For in the book of <hi>ordination</hi> (which wee have alſo by our ſubſcription approved) to the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi> ready to be ordered, is put this <hi>Queſtion; Will you reverently obey your Ordinary, and other chiefe miniſters to whom the government and charge of you ſhall be committed, following with a glad minde and will their godly admonitions &amp; judgements, &amp;c?</hi> The <hi>anſwer</hi> is <hi>affirmative</hi> and promiſſory; <hi>We will, the Lord being our helper:</hi> and this promiſe wee doe not only make, but ratifie in the oath of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical obedience, which on ſundry occaſions we take. So that every one of our tribe is held with a <hi>double</hi> bond. 1 A <hi>common</hi> bond of <hi>ſubjection</hi> to ſuperiours, as we are ſubordinate and <hi>inferiour</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: <hi rend="sup">2</hi> A <hi>particular</hi> bond of oath and promiſe, as wee are <hi>miniſters.</hi> Now if to <hi>break</hi> that <hi>generall</hi> bond of obedience which lies on all inferiours, be a <hi>violation</hi> of authority, a <hi>ſin</hi> to which the <hi>guilt of damnation</hi> is annexed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2. to breake that awfull tye of a <hi>vow</hi> and voluntary promiſe, muſt needs be a <hi>greater</hi> ſinne, and accompanied with a <hi>heavier</hi> guilt. Solemne and deliberat promiſes are not like <hi>Samſons</hi> green cords, eaſie to be ſnapt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder; but ſtrongly <hi>binde,</hi> either to <hi>performance,</hi> or <hi>puniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> if we fling off theſe conſiderations yet let <hi>reſpect</hi> to our peoples <hi>welfare</hi> (over whoſe ſouls
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:4314:37"/> we are ſet to <hi>watch,</hi> and for whom we muſt give an <hi>account) win</hi> us to obedience. How can the <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracing</hi> and <hi>impugning</hi> of good orders, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>factions</hi> and diviſions in the Church, ſtand with their good? Was it well with the <hi>Iews,</hi> when <hi>Korah</hi> and their <hi>Levites</hi> affronted their <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Prieſt, Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron?</hi> Did not the <hi>flame</hi> of Gods fiery indignation break out upon them for their diſloyalty and <hi>ſchiſme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.</note> to the deſtruction of a great part of the <hi>congregation?</hi> Can it bee well with the <hi>body,</hi> when the <hi>principall</hi> members con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire againſt their <hi>Heads,</hi> and will not be guided by them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Schiſme</hi> hath ever been the <hi>bane</hi> of <hi>Churches,</hi> and <hi>irregularity</hi> the <hi>beginner</hi> of <hi>Schiſme,</hi> yea of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie</hi> too, and all kinde of confuſion, if S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> may be beleeved, who attributes all the miſchiefs that uſually befall Churches to this <hi>Fury. Hac ſunt initia haereticorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cypr. cp. ad Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat.</note> (ſaith the Father) <hi>&amp; orius at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conatus ſchiſmaticorum malè cogitantium, ut ſibi placeant, ut praepoſitum ſuperbo tumore contemnant.</hi> Self-pleaſing pride, and ſcornfull deſpiſing of the heads of the Church, is the <hi>viper</hi> from which both <hi>ſchiſmes</hi> and <hi>hereſies</hi> draw their <hi>firſt breath.</hi> Let us therfore by <hi>our</hi> ſubmiſſion to our Churches Rites commend that humble obedience to our <hi>people,</hi> which they owe to their <hi>Fathers</hi> in Chriſt, their rulers in the Church.</p>
            <p>Next, we muſt looke to our <hi>people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">People per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded to obedience.</note> and winne them to a reverent reſpect, <hi>as</hi> of God and his laws, <hi>ſo</hi> of Gods <hi>Vicegerents</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and their ordinances. It is a <hi>hard</hi> task I confeſſe, to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:4314:38"/> draw a <hi>perverted,</hi> and <hi>prejudging</hi> multitude to a love and liking of ſuch things as croſſe their <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme.</hi> Some <hi>nobler</hi> ſpirits (perhaps) will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <hi>dediſcere benè quod didicerunt non benè,</hi> (as <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinenſis</hi> ſpeakes) to <hi>unlearne</hi> bad leſſons which they have been taught: but <hi>weaker</hi> mindes are (for the moſt part) too <hi>obſtinate</hi> retainers of the precepts and practiſes of their <hi>firſt</hi> breeders; as the <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Javen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at.</hi> 14.— V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us &amp; al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Forſitan <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpernant juvenes quibus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e benign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>— — <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t meliore luto ſinxit prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia Titan: Sed reliqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gienda patrum veſtig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ducunt, Et monſtrata diu veretis u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hit orbita cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pae.</note> 
               <hi>Poet</hi> could ſee, who therefore <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Id ibid.</hi> — Nil dictu faedum, viſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> haec <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng v—l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt. <hi>and</hi> —Maxima deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>everent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> counſells parents to be very carefull of what they ſay or do in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of their children. Wee uſe to ſay, that <hi>quartane</hi> agues, and <hi>hypocondriack</hi> diſeaſes, are <hi>lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibria medicorum,</hi> the <hi>reproaches</hi> of <hi>Phyſitians;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by reaſon of the ſtubborn humours that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get them, and the firm footing which they have taken in the body, they are ſeldome cured. What is ſaid of them, may as truly bee ſaid of this evill <hi>ſickneſſe</hi> of <hi>faction</hi> and undutifulneſſe; for where by the power of bad <hi>preſidents,</hi> the poyſon of bad <hi>principles,</hi> and its owne <hi>congruity</hi> to our proud and lawleſſe diſpoſitions, it hath gotten head, it will not eaſily yeeld up its poſſeſſion. Yet as Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>give not over</hi> ſuch patients, but by <hi>contempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> Juleps firſt, and by gentle purgatives next, <hi>lead</hi> out that <hi>ſtubborn</hi> ſtuffe which <hi>foments</hi> theſe maladies:<note place="margin">Yet muſt be attempted.</note> ſo muſt the <hi>ſervant</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> (whoſe duty is with <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>gentleneſſe</hi> to inſtruct the <hi>refractary,</hi> and <hi>waite,</hi> if God at any <hi>time</hi> will give them <hi>repentance,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24, 25.) Firſt by <hi>perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> more moderate and honourable conceits up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their people of governours and government, and then by <hi>convincing</hi> them with ſubſtantiall
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:4314:38"/> reaſons, of the <hi>decency</hi> of our preſcribed Rites, and the <hi>neceſsity</hi> of <hi>uſing</hi> them being <hi>enjoyned;</hi> endeavour to <hi>conjure</hi> out the evill ſpirit of preſumption, and to bring in the meek and good ſpirit of obedience.</p>
            <p>This is the ready way to bee <hi>ill thought</hi> of, (may ſome peradventure think or ſay) and (which is worſe) to be <hi>ill provided for too,</hi> and therefore <hi>Diana</hi> muſt not downe, diſobedience muſt be wincked at.</p>
            <p>It is moſt true indeed (witneſſe experience) that if a man once ſhew himſelf in the <hi>cauſe</hi> &amp; <hi>quarrell</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and doe but heartily <hi>wiſh</hi> for an <hi>unity</hi> &amp; <hi>unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> of opinion &amp; practiſe, that friends, maintenance, reſpect, all <hi>forſake</hi> him. And this is the cauſe why ſome cannot ſee the truth, others diſſemble their opinions in this particular. <hi>How can ye beleeve</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>who ſeek for honour one of another? Ioh.</hi> 5. Implying, that <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pularity</hi> is a <hi>blinder;</hi> it makes men <hi>unwilling to ſtudy</hi> ſuch doctrines as are in eſteeme with the people, <hi>leſt they</hi> ſhould <hi>ſee</hi> their falſhood, &amp; be <hi>forced</hi> to <hi>forſake</hi> them; and it <hi>perverts</hi> their underſtandings, and makes them judge with <hi>favour</hi> the <hi>Diana's</hi> of the people, and with <hi>rancour</hi> the <hi>contrary.</hi> As it puts out the eyes, ſo it <hi>ties</hi> the <hi>tongue,</hi> as we may ſee, Joh. 12.42, 43. <hi>Many of the chiefe rulers beleeved on him, but becauſe of the Phariſees they did not confeſſe him, leſt they ſhould be put out of the Synagogue. For they loved the praiſe of men more than the praiſe of God.</hi> As it made theſe rulers, ſo it makes a great many in our dayes <hi>diſſemble</hi> their judgement, and let their people go on in their heady and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient practiſes. But God keep filthy <hi>avarice</hi> and <hi>vain-glory</hi> from his own <hi>Portion.</hi> If by <hi>doing</hi> our duties, and <hi>ſeeking</hi> our peoples good and the Churches peace, we
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:4314:39"/> can get either <hi>name,</hi> or <hi>means,</hi> let us eſteeme it a <hi>preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> oyntment &amp; a bleſſing of God; but if we muſt loſe them, except we will <hi>diſſemble</hi> our opinions, <hi>deny</hi> our obedience, &amp; let our people run to ruine for want of warning and inſtruction, let them goe; the intereſt is too great, and he that makes this <hi>match,</hi> will be a <hi>loſer</hi> in the end; <hi>lucrum in crumenâ,</hi> this <hi>gain</hi> in the <hi>purſe,</hi> will be <hi>damnum in conſcientiâ, loſſe</hi> in the <hi>conſcience.</hi> We are the ſervants of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> by ſpeciall commiſſion, &amp; muſt not therefore be guided in our doings &amp; ſayings by <hi>popular</hi> humours; for Chriſt and the world are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary maſters; &amp; <hi>if we ſhould yet pleaſe men, we cannot bee the ſervants of Chriſt</hi> 
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10.</note>. It is a kinde of <hi>martyrdome</hi> to <hi>loſe</hi> any thing in a <hi>good</hi> cauſe, <hi>dulce eſt &amp; decorum eſt pro patria mori,</hi> it is an honourable thing to die for ones <hi>countrey,</hi> much more noble is it, for the good of the <hi>Church, mori mundo,</hi> to die to the world, and the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of it. And therefore with the <hi>woman</hi> in the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, trampling Luna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſublunaria,</hi> the <hi>moon</hi> &amp; all things <hi>beneath it</hi> under our <hi>feet,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſacrificing</hi> credit &amp; profit to <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>peace,</hi> let our beſt endeavour be to reſtore our <hi>ill-affected</hi> brethren &amp; people as <hi>obedient</hi> children to the <hi>Church,</hi> that ſo wee may <hi>ſerve the Lord</hi> (as the Prophet phraſeth it) <hi>with one ſhoulder,</hi> &amp; live together under our preſent <hi>happy government</hi> (which God of his mercy long continue) <hi>a peaceable and quiet life in all godlineſs &amp; honeſty.</hi> Which <hi>God</hi> grant for his <hi>Sons</hi> ſake. To whom with thee O <hi>Father,</hi> &amp; bleſſed Spirit, three glorious Perſons, and one eternall God, be rendred (as is moſt due) all honour, praiſe, and glory for <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
